In this demo, we'll take a look at working with user controls. So here's the project we'll be using,
and I've done a little bit of setup. I've added a class called Person; this class has FirstName, LastName,
and Age properties, and then in the load event for the form, I've created an instance of Person and set the properties.
And now what I want to do is create a user control that will work with the person data.
So I'll right-click on my project and choose Add, User Control; I'll call this the PersonControl.
And here we have the design surface, and we work with this just like we would with the form.
So let me resize it for now, and then open the Toolbox, and I want three TextBoxes, so 1, and then I'll
just copy and paste 2 and 3, and then I'll move these guys around a little bit.
And then I want three labels, so there's our Label, and then again just copy and paste a couple more,
and then now I can format the form a little bit. Okay, so this label's text will be First Name, and then this
TextBox will be called the FirstNameTextBox, and then I'll set the similar properties of the other controls,
and then come back to the video. And then I'll just move these controls a little bit, so I'm just going to
lasso all of them, they can go up into here, and then I'll resize the control to just take up that much space there.
Now we'll add the code for the control, so I'll right-click on the design area and choose View Code, I'll
unpin the Toolbox, and then I'll create a Person property here, so I'll use the Property code snippet,
and the name of our field will be _person, and this is of type Person, and the name of our Property will
also be Person, and again this is of type Person. And then in the Get I will return _person, but before I
do that I want to make sure that the values in the TextBoxes are reflected in the person object, so that
would be _person.FirstName = FirstTextBox.Text and _person.LastName = LastNameTextBox.Text and _person.Age =
CInt(ageTextBox.text). And then in the Set I'll do the reverse, so that'll be FirstTextBox.Text =
value.FirstName, and LastNameTExtBox.Text = Value.LastName, and AgeTextBox.Text = value.Age.
And for our simple demo that's sufficient, so now let's come over to the form,
and what I want to do is put a person control onto the form. So if I go to the Toolbox and then go up to
the top here, what I want to do is have the PersonControl show up over here in the Toolbox.
And the way I can get that is by building the project. So, I'll do Ctrl Shift B to build the project,
and then sometimes you need to Auto Hide and then reopen the Toolbox for this to show up; there we go,
there's our PersonControl, and then drag and drop that onto the form.
And I can move it around, I can put it with other controls; it's just like any other control.
And then over here in the form, what I want to do is just say PersonControl1.Person = p.
And then to show we're getting the values of the TextBoxes, actually let's just come back here and then put
down a button below this here, and then in the button Click event handler, let's write out the last name.
So, MsgBox(PersonControl1.Person.LastName). Alright, so let's press F5 to test out our work.
So there's our form with the person data, and right now if I click the button you can see the last name is
Windsor, and then if I change the last name to Smith and then click the button, you can see we get that value there.
So the process of building a user control is very similar to the process of building a form; it allows you
to consolidate commonly used UI and logic in one place.