The last section in this module is on Application Layouts. This is actually a preview of the upcoming
modules, because in those modules we'll build an application using each of the three common layouts or styles
of Windows Forms applications we'll be discussing here.
The first of these layouts is the Multiple Document Interface, or MDI. Here we have a single main form that contains some number of child forms.
This layout was very commonly used in the '90s into the early to mid-2000s, but it's sort of fallen out of
favor since then. Today you're more likely to see our second layout, which is the Single Document Interface,
or SDI application. SDI applications are similar in many ways to an MDI application, just without the main form.
So each of what would have been the child forms now becomes its own top-level form.
The final layout we'll take a look at is the Explorer-Style application; this gets its name because of the
similar look and feel to Windows Explorer. In these types of applications we'll have item selection on the
left-hand side of the form, and then we'll have the details for the item on the right-hand side of the form,
and it's very common to see developers use a tree view for items selection, and a list view to display the details.