In the last module we talked about events, but we focused on events for controls.
Forms also have events; most of these events relate to user interaction, for example, the user clicks on a
form, moves it, resizes it, and so on. But some of these events are related to the Lifecycle of the form,
and it's on these events that we'll focus in this section. The first pair of events we'll examine is
Load and Shown. Load fires after the constructor for the form is run, but just before the form is shown on
the screen, and Shown is fired after the form has been shown on the screen.
The load event is the event we'll handle for the form most often by far; it's generally used to populate the
data for controls and do any kind of conditional formatting. The form load event handler we see on the slide
is from a project we'll build later on in the course. The event handler we have in the upcoming demo is much simpler.
The next pair of events is Activated and Deactivate; these fire when the form gets focus and then loses focus.
We generally use these events to start and pause any Realtime processing.
And the final pair of events is Closing and Closed; closing fires just before the form is closed, and can be
cancelled and closed fires just after the form has been closed. In the demo we're about to see, we'll
implement the form load event, and then in the demo for the following section, after we talk a little bit
about dialogs, we'll see the implementation of the closing event and how to cancel the form closed.