In this demo we'll begin our examination of the form lifecycle, or form events; we'll take a look a look at
using the load event. Our examination will continue on in the next section after we talk a little bit about
dialogs, we'll take a look at the form closing event, and virtually all of the demos in the remainder of the
course will use the form events in some fashion. I've already laid out the form we're going to use for the
demo; it's basically the same as the form that we had at the end of the last module, the only difference is
that instead of a TextBox here at the top I have a ListBox, and then below that I have a button, and then
below that I have a label; you can't see the label because I've set its text property to be empty, but if I
come over to the Properties Window, and in the dropdown at the top I choose Label1, then there you can see
the label right there. So as I mentioned in the slides, the load event is the event we'll handle most often
for the form, so to add its event handler I can just double-click on the form anywhere outside of its controls,
and the title bar is a good place to do that because we can't put controls on the title bar.
So we just double-click here, and you can see we get the event handler for the form load event.
This event is most commonly used to put data inside controls. So normally we'll go to a database or maybe
call a web service, or get information from another system, like even the Windows File System, as we'll see
later on, and then we'll take that data and put it into the controls, most often using a process called Data Binding.
But since we haven't covered any of those topics yet, we'll just manually add some items into the ListBox.
So let me go into full screen, and then it's ListBox1; in this case I didn't give the controls meaningful
names, so we have ListBox1, Button1, and Label1. And it has a property called Items, which is its items
collection, and into the items we want to Add, and we'll just put the names of some fruits here, so Oranges.
And then I'm going to call this a few times, so let me just paste a few more items in here, and then we'll
put in Grapes, and then how about Bananas, and then finally how about Peaches.
Okay. So the variable for the control, the creation of the control, setting properties like location and
size, that's all still being done in Initialize Component in the designer file, we're just actually setting
the data that goes into the control here in form load. We also want to add the event handler for the click
of the button, so let me get Button1 here, and then go at its Click event handler.
And in here we want to take the text for the selected item in the ListBox and put it into the label.
So that's Label1.Text = ListBox1, and the text for the selected item, the property name is just Text.
With these events implemented, I can now run the program, so I'll press F5, and we can see there are fruit
names in the ListBox, and I can select one of these, and then click Show Selected Item, and then that text
will show down here in the label. So that's a simple example of form load.
As I mentioned previously, we'll see other examples, more complex examples, as we go on throughout the course
and we'll also see the implementation of the form closing event in the next demo.
Now there is one more topic I want to cover; it's not really related to the form lifecycle, but it is
important overall for the course. So if I come over to my running form, and I resize it, you notice that the
controls just sort of stay where they are. And if I resize it larger or if I resize it smaller, you can see
we actually can't see some of the controls now. So let me show you how we can address this issue using the
Anchor property of the controls.
If I get out of full screen, and then go to the Designer, we have our three controls, there's a label which
is kind of down here, and then we have our button, and we have our ListBox.
So what I want to do is as I resize the form, as this grows here, I want the label to stay relative to the
bottom left of the form, and I want the button to also stay relative to the bottom left, and I want the
ListBox to grow or shrink with the form. And I could indicate that I want these things to happen using the
anchor property of the controls. So I'll click on the ListBox, and then we'll scroll up to Anchor.
And you can see by dropping this down here that it's currently anchored to the top right of the form.
Well, as I mentioned, I want the ListBox to grow and shrink as the form grows and shrinks, so I'm going to
anchor it on all four points, which means keep the relative difference between the left, right, top, and
bottom of the control to the form. So I want this distance to remain consistent, I want that distance to
remain consistent, and the same thing over here. And then for the button and for the label, I want the
relative distance from here and here to remain the same, so I want them to go down as the form grows,
and then go up as the form shrinks. So again, I'll go find the Anchor property, and then I'll say that I
want to anchor them bottom left. And for the label again because I can't see it, I'll just select it here
out of the dropdown, and put Anchor, and go bottom left. Alright, now I'll run again, and then now as I grow
my form, we see it remains sort of the same look and feel, behavior obviously remains the same, and then if
I shrink the form, then the behavior and look and feel remain the same.
So that's anchoring controls. In a later demo we'll see the use of docking controls, where we can dock a
control to the top of the form, the side, bottom, or we can have the control take up the entire space of the form.