In this section we'll take a look at working with Dialogs. Dialogs are forms that either provide information
to the user or request information from the user. Dialogs are almost always modal, meaning that you can't
switch from the dialog to the other forms on the application; the only way you can get back to the other
forms is by closing the dialog. Windows Forms includes several dialog types we can use; we'll see the use
of MessageBox in the upcoming demo, and we'll see the use of the OpenFile and SaveFile dialogs in a demo
later on in the course. We could also create our own custom dialogs; we'll see this in the next section.
To show a simple dialog on the screen, we can us VB's MsgBox function or we can use the Show method of the
MessageBox type that's in a System.Windows.Form namespace. For more complex dialogs, we'll create an
instance of the dialog type and set its properties, and then we'll display the dialog using the ShowDialog
method of the form type. The ShowDialog method is expected to return a member of the DialogResult enumeration.
This value represents the button the user clicked to close the dialog.
So taking a look at the snippet on this slide that uses the SaveFile dialog, when the dialog closes, we check
to see whether or not the user clicked the OK button, and then if they did, we save the contents of the
RichTextBox to the file the user selected in the dialog. The name of that file is exposed through the file
name property of the dialog type.