In this demo we'll take a look at working with dialogs. So here I have a project, it's a different project,
but the form is the same as the form from the last demo; I have the ListBox, the button, and the label.
If we take a look at the code behind, we have the same event handlers.
And if I run this, and just click the button right away, you notice there's no text in the label, and the
reason for that is there is no selected item in the ListBox, so the text property is empty.
Now if I actually go and select an item from the ListBox and then click the button, now we get the text down
here in the label. So what I want to do is add some code in the Click event handler for the button to check
to see whether or not there is the selected item in the ListBox, and if there isn't, let the user know they
need to select an item first before clicking the button.
So let's take a look at the code. What I could do is check the text property to see if that's empty, but the
more proper way, or more common way to check to see whether the ListBox has a selected item or not, is to
check the selected index property. So this property gives you the index of the item that's currently
selected, but if there isn't a currently selected item, it will give you back -1.
So you could write here: If ListBox1.SelectedIndex = -1, then I want to show the user or give the user a
message telling them that they need to select an item out of the ListBox.
So the message I want to show the user is "Please select an item from the list box," and now I just need some
way to put that up on the screen. And to do that I'm going to use the MsgBox function, this has been part of
the Visual Basic language probably as far back as VB1, but if not, definitely the early days of Visual Basic.
And then the one parameter I need to pass into this is what message do you want to show to the user,
and that's the message "Please select an item from the list box."
And then once I've shown the user that message, I just want to exit out of the Sub to let them select an item
and then click the button again. Alright, so let's run again, and I won't select an item, I'll click the
button, so there's our MessageBox, Please select an item from the list box, we have an OK button, the title
of the dialog is the same name as our project, so we'll click OK. And then if I select an item, then it
works as before. Now, MsgBox is a Visual Basic function, it's part of the Visual Basic language.
So while technically you could use this in C# by adding a reference to the Microsoft.VisualBasic assembly,
it's extremely unlikely that anybody would do that. Instead they'd use the MsgBox class that's in the
System.Windows.Forms namespace. We can also use the MsgBox class in Visual Basic, so let me comment out this
line, and then replace it using the MsgBox class, so that would be MessageBox.Show; it has a shared method
called Show, and Show takes the message you want to show to the user, so that's msg.
Now in the case of the MessageBox, the title by default is empty, so we want to specify that, and again the
title in MsgBox, is just the title of the form, the main form, so I'll just pass that in, such as Me.Text.
So now I'll run again and click the button, and we get exactly the same behavior we had when using MsgBox.
So that's presenting information to a user, what about asking the user a question?
Well we can use the same functionality to do that. So let's go and add an event handler for the form closing event.
So I'll drop down here and I'll go to Form1 Events, and then the event I want is actually FormClosing.
And then here I want to put up one of those "Are you sure?" dialogs to ask the user if they're sure they want
to leave the program. So here I want to ask: "Are you sure you want to close?"
And then I want to put up a dialog box where they can choose Yes or No.
So that's If MsgBox and then the message, and then here I have an option to say what buttons or what style
I want to show for the MessageBox. But, the option I want to choose out of here is MsgBoxStyle.YesNo,
so I want to show both Yes and No buttons to the user. And as you can see in the IntelliSense here that this
is going to return a MsgBox result. So I'm going to check to see, does = MsgBoxResult.No.
And if it does, then I want to cancel the close of the form. So if you take a look, the EventArgs we're
getting here are FormClosingEventArgs, and for most of the events in .NET that end with ing, you can cancel
them, and the way you cancel is just by putting e.Cancel = true. Alright, so let's run, hit F5, and then
I'll try to close the form, Are you sure you want to close? Yes, the form closes, hit F5, Are you sure you
want to close? No, and then the form stays open. And then just like in the previous example, if I choose
to use MessageBox.Show instead of MsgBox, then the code I would write would look like this.
MessageBox.Show, the message I want to show, the caption for the dialog, what buttons I want to show;
in this case instead of MessageBoxStyle it is the System.Windows.Forms.MessageBoxButtons enumeration,
and then for the response, instead of MessageBoxResult, it's System.Windows.Forms.DialogResult.
So that's how you use the built-in message dialogs. In the next section we'll take a look at how to build
a custom message dialog.