Now that we've seen how to show simple dialogs using the built-in functionality of the .NET framework,
let's take a look at how to build Custom Dialogs. You create a custom dialog as you would any other Windows form.
You add the form to the project, you add controls to the form, you set their properties, and add their event handlers.
There are just a few additional properties you need to set to make your form look, feel, and behave like a dialog.
The first of these is the FormBorderStyle, which you'll want to set to FixedDialog; this changes the visual
style of the border and disables resizing of the form.
Next you'll want to set the ControlBox property to false; this removes the minimize, maximize, and close
buttons in the title bar of the form. And then finally you'll want to set the Accept and Cancel buttons.
Setting one of the buttons on the form to be the AcceptButton means that if the user presses Enter,
that's the same as them clicking the button. And setting the button to be the Cancel button means that if
the user presses the Escape key, that's the same as clicking the button.
And then finally, when the user does click one of the buttons, you want to set the return value for the dialog.
You can do this in one of two ways; you can do it in the event handler for the button click, or if the only
thing you want to do when the user clicks the button is set the return value, then you can use the
DialogResult property of the button. One important thing to note is as soon as you set the DialogResult property of a
dialog, the dialog will close. So if you're doing this in the event handler, make sure that setting the
dialog result is the last line of code in the event handler Sub routine.