In this demo we'll build a custom dialog. I have a new project, but the form is the same as in the last project.
So I press F5, and then try to close the form, I'll get a dialog box, it has the text, Are you sure you want to close?
It has two buttons, Yes and No. If I click Yes or press Enter, the form will close; if I click No or press
Escape it won't. And what I want to do in this demo is build a custom dialog to replace the one we're using here.
I have the form for our custom dialog partially completed, so it created, I went to the project, right-click
Add, Windows Form, I called the form the Confirm dialog, I resized the form, I added a Panel control from
down here in the containers, and I docked it to the top, and then set its background color to white so we get
this, and then I added a label, put the text in, Are you sure you want to close?
I added two buttons, so this button is called the Yes button, and this button is called the No button.
And now what I want to do is set the properties of the form in the controls so that it really takes on the
role of a dialog. So let me unpin the toolbox here. So we'll start out with the properties of the form.
The first thing I want to do is set the border style to indicate visually that this is a dialog and also so
the form can't be resized, and that's the FormBorderStyle property.
I want to change that from Sizable, which is the default, to FixedDialog.
The next thing I want to do is remove the ability to minimize, maximize, or close using the control box.
So I'll go to the ControlBox property, and I'll set that to False.
And then finally I want to indicate that the Yes button is the accept button, meaning that pressing the Enter
key is the equivalent of clicking the button, and that the No button is the Cancel button, meaning that
pressing Escape is the same as clicking the button. So I'll come up, well actually we have a CancelButton
right here, so I'll say the CancelButton is the NoButton, and then I'll scroll up and we have the
AcceptButton, and that is the YesButton. And then the last thing I need to do to complete the dialog,
is indicate that if the user selects Yes by either clicking the button or pressing Enter, that the dialog
result is Yes, or if they choose No that the dialog result is equal to No.
Now I could do this by adding event handlers for the Yes or No buttons, but if the only thing we want to do
when the user clicks Yes or No is actually to set the DialogResult, then we can do that through properties of
the buttons themselves. So if I click on the Yes button, and then come over here, I can set the DialogResult
property to be Yes, and I can do the same thing for the No button, set the DialogResult property here to be No.
So with our dialog completed, we can now come over to
our code behind and modify it to use our new dialog. So here I'll change this variable to be a variable for
the dialog, so Dim dialog As New ConfirmDialog, and then down here, instead of using MsgBox, we just need to
say Dialog.ShowDialog. And then instead of checking for MsgBoxResult.No, we want to check for DialogResult.No.
Alright, so we're ready to test out our work, let's press F5, and then try to close the form, there's our
dialog, if I click Yes the form closes, press F5; try to close the dialog, click No, form doesn't close,
click Yes it does. So a good deal of the process of building a custom dialog is the same as building any
other Windows Forms, there are just a few extra properties of the form and the controls that you need to be aware of.