In this section we'll take a look at Menus and Toolbars. We'll start by looking at Menus.
The menu is implemented by the MenuStrip control, and the menu items are implemented by the
ToolStripMenuItem controls. Once you've added a MenuStrip to your form, you can add and edit items inline.
Once you've added the items you want, you can set their properties and handle their events using
the Properties Window. The three key properties of a menu item are the Text, Image, and ShortCutKeys.
When setting the text, which is the caption of the menu item, you can prefix one of the characters with ampersand (&amp;).
This makes that character the quick key, meaning that the user can either open the menu if it's a top level
menu, or select the menu item if it's a child by using the Alt key plus the quick key.
You can also assign a ShortCutKey to a menu item. This is generally something in combination with the Ctrl key,
but that's not required. And when a menu item has a ShortCutKey, you can run the event handler for that menu
item anywhere in the application using the ShortCutKey combination.
And finally, you can associate an image with the menu item using image property.
Commonly used images are available in the Visual Studio image library.
For Visual Studio 2010 and earlier, this comes as part of the install for Visual Studio; for Visual Studio
2012 it's a separate download.
Most applications that have a Menu will also have a Toolbar; this is another way to get quick access to
the menu functionality. We can add a toolbar to our form using the ToolStrip control.
The most common control you'll add to a ToolStrip is the button, or more specifically the ToolStrip button,
but you can also add Labels, TextBoxes, ComboBoxes, ProgressBars, and more.
One thing to note about the controls in the ToolStrip is they're actually a wrapper around the controls
we normally use. For example, you could add a ComboBox to the ToolStrip, or more specifically a ToolStripComboBox,
and this is just a wrapper around the ComboBox. So many of the properties and events of the ComboBox are
surfaced by the ToolStripComboBox, but not all of them. So sometimes you'll need to get access to the
underlying control, and each of the different ToolStrip controls has a property which gives you that access.
Now while I've been talking about Menus and Toolbars, you may have asking yourself, what about the Ribbon?
Many applications today use the Ribbon instead of Menus and Toolbars.
There are no Ribbon controls in the .NET framework, or more specifically Windows Forms, so we're not covering
it in this course. However, you do have options if you want to use the Ribbon.
Several of the third-party control suites include Ribbon controls, and there's also a Windows Forms wrapper
around the unmanaged functionality available from the Windows SDK.
This is a CodePlex project you can find at windowsribbon.codeplex.com.
Now I don't want to spend too much time on what we're not covering, so let's get back to what we are
covering, which is a demo of the introduction to Menus and Toolbars.