In this demo we'll take a look at working with Menus and Toolbars.
So here I have a freshly created Windows Forms project, and let's add a Menu, so I'll come over to the Toolbox,
and then in Menus &amp; Toolbars, I'll drag and drop a MenuStrip control onto my form.
And as I mentioned in the slides, I can add the items inline here in the Designer.
So let's add a File Menu, so that's &amp;File, and putting the ampersand(&amp;)character beside the F character means
that F is now the quick key, so I can open up this menu by pressing Alt F.
And now let's add some standard items under File, so &amp;New, &amp;Open, and now I want Save, but I want a separator
between open and save, so I'll put the - key and press Enter, and then &amp;Save Enter, and then Save &amp;As, Enter, and so on.
And if I wanted to add an Edit Menu, I could come up to the top and add &amp;Edit, and then below add its
children, and then put Tools, and add its children, and so on. Alright, so let's come back to the File Menu
and then for the menu items inside of the File Menu, I can add a shortcut, and I can add an image.
But before I do that, I want you to notice the names the designer has given the controls, so this is the new
ToolStrip menu item, this is Open, this is Save, this is Save As.
So instead of using the standard convention where it's ToolStrip Menu item 1, ToolStrip Menu item 2,
the designer has given the menu items meaningful names. Alright, so let's come back up to New, and let's set
it's ShortCutKey; normally that's Ctrl N. So, I'll come in the Properties Window and scroll down to
ShortCutKeys, and then here I'll open up the Designer, and I want this to be Ctrl N, so I'll click Ctrl,
and then under Keys I'll select N, and that's right there. And I also want to associate an image with this menu item.
You can get commonly used images in the Visual Studio Image Library.
If you're using Visual Studio 2012,
this is a download, so just do a search for Visual Studio 2012 Image Library, and download this.
If you're using Visual Studio 2010 or earlier, this comes as a Zip file with the product installation.
Alright, I've downloaded the Visual Studio 2012 Image Library; I put it in My Documents under Visual Studio 2012;
here's the Image Library, and it comes with lots of images. So the common ones here are in Actions, and you
have these as bmp files, icons, png files, and if you go over to png files, we can scroll down here; I don't
know, let's find Save, so there's the Save icon.
And notice it's the black and white icon, so this is the Visual Studio 2012 sort of black and white colorless theme.
If you want the colored icons you can find them in the archive here; and what I've done to save time is I've
just gone throughout these folders and grabbed the images we're going to use in the demos.
So I have the standard Edit, Cut, Copy, Paste, I'm using the colored ones here, I have things like Open,
New, this one called Document, and so on. So we'll use these. So I'll copy this path to the folder,
and then come over to Visual Studio, and then let's go find the Image property, and then open up to the Designer here.
And when I import an image, I have a choice of storing it in a Project Wide Resource file or a Form Specific
Resource file; I'll use the one that's Project Wide, so I'll click the Import button, and then put the path
into the folder I mentioned, and then let's bring in the Document I'll be using that for New.
So click OK, so now we can see we have the New image, and then come over to Open, and then go to its image,
Import, and then Open here, click OK, and then go to Save, and then find Image, Import, Save, and click OK.
So that covers adding a Menu and Menu Items to your form. Now let's take a look at adding a Toolbar.
So I'll click on the form, and I'll come back over to Menus &amp; Toolbars, and I'll add a ToolStrip control.
And as I mentioned on the slides, we can add several kinds of controls to the toolbar; the most commonly
used are buttons. So let's add a button for New, let's add a button for Open, one for Save, then let's add
a separator, and then here we can put Cut, Copy, and say Paste. So here are the buttons, let's configure
this one for New. Now we didn't get a meaningful name here, so I need to rename this to the new ToolStripButton.
And then I want to set its image, so let's scroll down here to the Image property, and click on here,
and we'll use the Project resource file, and New was Document, so we'll click OK, and that's really all we need.
I could set the text, so down here I could set this to be New, but for a button we don't normally use the caption.
But what you could set, which is valuable, is the ToolTipText, which shows when the user hovers over the
button, and we can set that to be the same as the text. And with that done I could now go do the same thing
for the other buttons, but I think you get the idea. In this demo I'm not going to show you how to use the
other kinds of controls on the ToolStrip, but in later demos we will see the use of the ComboBox.
Alright, so the last thing to cover is adding events, so let's add an event for the New menu item; so I'll
click on that, and then I can come over to the Properties Window, switch to the Events view, and then add
the Click event handler. So let's do something simple, let's just put up a MsgBox("You clicked New"),
and then come back over to the Designer, let's press F5, and then click File, New, and there is our message box.
And then now that we have the event handler for the menu item, we also want to associate the same event
handler for our toolbar button, so I can click on it, and then come over to the Properties Window, and then
instead of adding an event handler here, I'll select the one that we already have.
The ToolbarButtons Click event handler and the ToolStripMenuItem Click event handler have the same signature
so we can have the same event handler handle both events. So now if I press F5, and click the button in the
toolbar, you can see we get the same result. So that's the basics of using the menus and toolbars.
We'll see more on their use in the demos throughout the rest of the course.