SDI applications are like MDI applications, just without the main form.
So what would have been a child form in an MDI application becomes a top level form in an SDI application.
SDI applications are single instance, meaning that once the program is running, if the user tries to start
another instance of the program, all that happens is a new form is created in the running instance.
Because of this, the program continues to run until the last form is closed.
When building an SDI application using Visual Basic, we can get all this functionality just by properly
configuring the application framework.
When building an SDI application in C#, we can still use the application framework even though it's part of
Visual Basic; we just don't get the Visual Studio integration that VB apps do, and we don't get the same kind
of code generation. So in the C# application, we'll need to create a custom application object that inherits
from WindowsFormsApplicationBase. The WindowsFormApplicationBase type is part of the Microsoft.VisualBasic assembly.
Aside from the creation and/or configuration of the application object, building an SDI application is very
similar to building an MDI application. We'll see this in the upcoming series of demos.