In this demo we'll create the project and the form for our SDI application.
So in Visual Studio I'll choose File-New-Project, and then I'll choose the Windows Forms Application template,
and we'll call our project SDI, click OK, and then for the form that's given to us we'll rename this to DocForm,
so right-click on the Form-Rename, and then DocForm, press Enter; we want to rename both the file and the
class, so we'll choose Yes here. We'll make the form a little bit larger, and we'll change the title of the
form to New Document. And then what we want to do is go over to our MDI application; I have the main form
open, and I want to copy the menu and the toolbar from the form here to the form here.
In our SDI application there will be no main form, so each of the document forms has its own menu and toolbar.
So I'll come over to MDI, I'll click on the Menu, copy that to the clipboard, come over here and paste.
And then I'll come back to the MDI application, click on the toolbar, again copy, and paste.
And then finally I want a RichTextBox control to take up the remainder of the form, so I'll come over to
Common Controls, grab the RichTextBox, drag and drop it on the form, and dock it, and then rename it to
the DocumentTextBox. Alright, so at this point I have a program I could execute; I can click the Start
button and we'll see we get a form here; obviously it doesn't do anything yet.
But it's also not an SDI application. We need to configure the properties of the application object,
and we'll see that that's very simple to do in VB because of the application framework; it takes a little bit more code in C#.