In this demo we'll configure the application object for the Visual Basic version of our SDI project.
This process is relatively easy because of Visual Basic's application framework.
So to access the application framework properties I can go to the project's properties, I can do that by
right-clicking my project and selecting Properties, or just double-clicking on the MyProject node.
And then in the Application tab, we have the startup form, and then we have the application framework properties.
The startup form is already set to DocForm, that's what I want, and then here in the application framework
properties, I want to make this a single instance application, meaning that if the user tries to run the
application, but there's already an instance running, it won't try to create a second one.
And I want to change the shutdown mode to when the startup form closes to when the last form closes.
So if I save this off and then go to the Solution Explorer and choose Show All Files, then under My Project,
we have MyApplication.myapp, and inside of there we have Application.Designer.vb, and here's where we can
see the result of the changes we made. So here in the MyApplication class, we have the constructor,
and here's where we can see setting the single instance property on, here's where we can see the change to
the shutdown style, that is now after all forms close, and here's where we can see how the startup form gets set.
Now this method, OnCreateMainForm, is responsible for showing the form when the application first starts up,
but the user might try to start up another instance of the application, and we need to tell the program what
to do in that case. So if I get out of full screen,
and then go back to the Properties, we can see here in the application framework properties, there's this
button, View Application Events. So, if I turn off Show All Files, and then I click that button, you'll see
now we'll get a file ApplicationEvents.vb. And you'll see that there are several events we can handle,
Startup, actually, let me get into the full screen here, so Startup, Shutdown, UnhandledException,
StartupNextInstance, and NetworkAvailabilityChanged. So we're interested in this case in handling the
StartupNextInstance event. So I'll come into the MyApplication class, and then I'll drop down here and
choose the events, and then here I'll choose the StartupNextInstance event.
And what I want to do here is create a new instance of the DocForm and show it, but I'm going to be using
that same code in a few different places, so I'm going to centralize it inside of the DocForm itself.
So let me get out of full screen, save my work, and then go to DocForm here, and then right-click and choose
to View Code. And the code we want is similar to the code we had in our MDI program, so let's go back over
there, and then let's go to the code for the main form; we can see the code here, so I'll just copy and paste it;
actually let's just do it piece by piece, so let's do the field first.
Come back over here, and paste that in, and then I want to create a function called CreateForm, so that will
be Public Function CreateForm As DocForm, and then we'll go back over to the MDI application,
and then grab this code, and come back over here and paste it, and then just modify it.
So we'll change this from chidlForm to form, and we'll change this from childForm to DocForm.
We don't need to set the MdiParent, so I can remove that. I do want to increment the counter, I do want
to change the Text property, and I do want to Show the form.
And then the last thing I want to do is change this to a shared function, because this creates and instance
of the DocForm, but right now I can only call it if I have an instance of the DocForm, but if I had an
instance of the DocForm I wouldn't need to call the method, so I wouldn't be able to call this just by having the type,
so we'll change this to Shared Function, and that means I also need to change this field to a Shard field.
And then two final changes, this is a function, so I just need to return the form that I've created,
so that's just Return form. And also, each time I create a new form, it's going to be the form that has
prominence, so I want to indicate that it's the main form of the application or becomes the main form of the application.
So here I'll add, My.Application, this gives me access to the application object, and then I want to set the
main form property. Well, the application object itself doesn't have a main form property, but it has an
application context, and that has a main form property, and it's that that we'll set.
And now I can go back to my ApplicationEvents, and then here in my event handler I can say DocForm.CreateForm,
and that will create a new instance of the DocForm and show it on the screen.
Alright, so to see this in action, let's build our project, and then let's minimize everything here,
and let's come over to where our project is, so that is Visual Studio 2012-Projects-SDI-bin-Debug,
and then let's take this guy and let's send that to the Desktop as a shortcut, and then come over
to our Desktop here, and actually let's startup the Task Manager, and let's sort these backwards,
because SDI is going to be here. So you have SDI.vshost, that's the one that's running inside of Visual Studio.
Now let's double-click on the SDI shortcut; there we see the SDI application running that's hosting this form,
right, and if I double-click on the shortcut again, now we see the next document come up, but notice there is
no other instance of SDI. So the same application instance that handled the first form is handling the second form.
You can see that every time I double-click here, we get a new form created, but we only have a single instance.
And then if I go and close all of these, there you can see that the SDI application goes away.
So that's configuring the application object in VB. C# doesn't have the application framework, but we could
actually use the base types from the Microsoft.VisualBasic namespace in our C# application to get the same
behavior; we're just going to have to write about 20 or 30 lines of code to replace the settings that we set
in our VB application; we'll see that next.