In this demo I want to create and configure the application object for the C# version of our SDI project.
Here's the C# project, and so far I have the form, and I've added the menu, the toolbar, and the Rich TextBox;
I haven't done anything else yet. What I want to do now is add an application object that uses the
application framework functionality we saw in the VB version of the demo.
But since the application framework is part of the VB language, we're not going to have any Visual Studio
integration here in a C# project, so I'll have to write that code manually.
So I'll right-click on the project and choose Add-Class, I'll call the class SdiApplication, and just like
the other application objects we've seen, I want this to be a singleton.
So here I have a field which we'll use to hold the singleton instance, and then I have a property we can use
to access the instance. This checks to see if the instance has been created yet; if it hasn't it creates it;
if it has it just returns it. So as long as we only access SdiApplication through this instance property,
we'll never have more than one instance of the object at any given time.
So that makes SdiApplication a singleton; now we want to make it an application, one that implements the
application framework functionality. To do that, we'll have it inherit from WindowsFormsApplicationBase.
This type lives in the Microsoft.VisualBasic assembly, so we'll need to add an assembly reference.
So in the Framework section, Microsoft.VisualBasic, and then come back over here and indicate this inherits
from WindowsFormsApplicationBase. And then we just need to add the appropriate using statement,
that's Microsoft.VisualBasic.ApplicationServices. Next we'll add a constructor and set some properties.
So we'll come in here after the field, add the constructor. Now what properties do we need to set?
Well if we go back to our Visual Basic project, and then take a look at the project properties, we made two
changes; we set the Make single instance application on, or we checked that check box, and we changed the
Shutdown mode to When the last form closes. If we take a look at the generated code,
we can see here in the application object we have the setting of the IsSingleInstance to true, and setting of
the ShutDownStyle to ShutdownMode.AfterAllFormsClose. So we do the same thing here, so this.IsSingleInstance,
I'm going to set that = true, and then this.ShutdownStyle = ShutdownMode.AfterAllFormsClose.
The other thing we had in our VB project that we need to add to the C# project was handling of two events.
One was OnCreateMainForm; this was part of the generated code that we got, and the second is to handle the
StartupNextInstance, we added this through the application events.
And in both cases what we want to do is call the CreateForm helper method that we added to the DocForm.
So coming back to the C# project, let's go into full screen here, and then let's override those two methods,
so override OnCreateMainForm, and then override OnStartup next instance, and again in both cases we just want
to call DocForm.CreateForm.
(typing)
And now we just need to go implement CreateForm.
So if we go to full screen, and then go over to DocForm and view the code, below the constructor here,
we can add the implementation of CreateForm. So, we have a field for the counter, and then in CreateForm
we create a new instance of the DocForm, we set the form title using the counter.
We then set the form we just created to be the MainForm for the application, we Show the form and we return
the form reference. So with the implementation of the CreateForm helper added, our SDI application class
is now complete; oops, actually it's not complete because I added the wrong override here, let me fix that.
I wanted to override OnStartup next instance, not OnStartup; so we'll just take this code here and we'll cut
it and we'll paste it over here, and then we'll just get rid of this guy; okay, now it's complete.
So the final thing we need to do is modify the startup code for the application, so come over to program,
and we need to replace Application.Run with SdiApplication.Instance.Run, and this actually takes a parameter
here, which is the command line arguments, so we just need to change Main to accept those, so it's an array
of string, and we'll call it args, and then we'll pass that over here.
So that's everything we need to convert the Windows Forms application into an SDI application; let's test out our work.
So I'll go ahead and build, and then we'll minimize this, and we'll come over to the SDI project folder,
and then we'll right-click on the executable, and Send To Desktop, creating a shortcut,
and then we'll click here; actually, before I do that, let me just startup Task Manager.
So we see SDICS.vshost, again that's the one running in Visual Studio.
Now we run here, so we should now see SDICS.exe, and then let's run again using the shortcut, there we go,
New Document 2, run again, New Document 3, run again, New Document 4, but all using the same executable,
and then if I close these down, once I close the last one, the executable should go away.
So with the addition of the application object complete, in the next demo we'll move on to the implementation
of the menu items.