In this demo we'll implement the File and Edit menu options in our SDI application.
So we've already added the menu in the toolbar, but we haven't implemented any of the event handlers yet,
so if I go over to the MDI application, again there are a lot of similarities here, so all I'll do is just
go and copy and paste all of the File and Edit event handlers we had; see Undo, Cut, Copy, Paste, SelectAll,
okay that would be those, and then come over here and paste those in; let's paste them above our CreateForm function.
And now let's go and fix up their implementations. Okay, so for File-New, we have our CreateForm method,
so I can just call that, and then for Open, we still want to show the OpenFileDialog; when the user clicks OK
we want to put the contents of the file that they chose, let me go into full screen, into the DocumentTextBox
of the current form not a new form. So that would be Me.DocumentTextBox.LoadFile, and then Me.Text = dialog.FileName.
For Close we're going to close the current form, so that will be Me.Close.
For Save we don't need to get the ActiveChild form, we're going to save the contents of our DocumentTextBox,
so let's just go and remove that If statement that surrounds this, and then here again this changes from
ChildForm to Me. Since there isn't a MainForm, we'll remove the Exit menu handler or Exit menu, so let me
just remove the event handler here, and then go back to the form and just get rid of this separator, and then
get rid of the Exit menu. So that completes the File menu, and now we should be into the Edit menu.
And here again we don't have to worry about the ActiveMdiChild, so let's just delete that and that, and then
it's just Me. So I'll just grab this and come down here, paste that in, change Undo to Redo, and then do
the same for Cut, Copy, Paste, and then finally SelectAll. Now in VB, because we have the handles clause on
our event handlers, our event handlers will be attached to the events automatically.
In C# you'll have to go back to the form, click on each of the events, and then using the Events view here,
go and attach them. So now if we hit F5, then we can create a new document using the toolbar, we can create
a new document using the menu, we can open one of the files we had before, we can save, here I'll save over
top of one of the other documents, we can close the form, so come over here File-Close, we can select all
the text, we can cut, undo that cut, we can redo that cut, we can paste, we can copy, and then we can paste again.
So that's the implementation of the File and Edit menus. For the Window menu we're not going to have
Cascade, Tile Horizontally, or Tile Vertically, but we do want to have the dropdown which shows all of the
open windows and allows us to switch between them. Now because we're in an SDI application and not an MDI
application, we won't get that functionality automatically; we'll have to write some code in an event handler
to do that, and that will be the next demo.