In this demo we'll complete the implementation of our SDI application by implementing the Window menu.
As I mentioned in the previous demo, we won't be having the Cascade, Tile Horizontally, and Tile Vertically
menu options, but we do want the Window menu option, and when the user clicks this, we want to show a list
of the open forms or open documents and allow the user to switch between them.
This functionality was provided for us automatically in the MDI application, but here in the SDI application
we'll have to implement it ourselves. So we'll do that in the event handler for the Windows DropDownOpening
event; that's this guy right here. When this event fires, we want to check to see if the Window menu option
has any children, so has the user clicked on the Window menu option previously?
If they have, we want to remove the existing items, and then go to the application object, find the current
list of open forms, and then repopulate the children of the Window menu item.
So the first step is to check to see if there are already children, and if there are remove them, so that's
If the WindowToolStripMenuItem.DropDownITems.Count &gt; 0 Then, and what we could do here is go and remove each
item individually, but there's actually a property called DropDown which contains the menu items, we can just
go ahead and remove that and then recreate it. So that's WindowToolStripMenuItem.DropDown.Dispose.
And then down here, once we know there are no children we'll recreate the DropDown, so
WindowToolStripMenuItem.DropDown = New ToolStripDropdown. Now we'll go through the list of open forms For
Each openForm As Form In My.Application.OpenForms, we'll create a new menu item to represent the form,
so Dim childItem As New ToolStripMenuItem, and then we'll set the text of the menu item to be the title of
the form, so childItem.Text = openForm.Text. And we also want to keep a reference to the form object,
we'll use that in the Click event handler for the menu item. To do that we'll need a property of the control
we can use to store the reference, and each control actually has a property called Tag, which you can use for
whatever purpose you want; you can store an object reference in there, you can store a value in there;
so we'll go ahead and use that. So it's childItem.Tag = openForm.
Then we need to add our new menu item to the dropdown items for the Window menu,
so that's WindowToolStripMenuItem.DropDownItems.Add(childItem).
And the last thing to do is hook up the Click event handler for our menu item, so that when the user clicks
on it, it will activate the associated form. So that's AddHandler childItem.Click, AddressOf, and the name
we'll give our event handler is WindowMenuItemClick. So now down here we'll implement the event handler,
so that's Private Sub WindowMenuItemClick, here let me just scroll up a little bit, and then we have
(sender As Object, e As EventArgs). When this gets called, sender will be a reference to the menu item that
was clicked, so let's get a variable to represent that that's properly typed,
so that's Dim menuItem = CType(sender, ToolStripMenuItem), and then the Tag property of the menu item
contains a reference to the form, but Tag is typed as object, so we'll have to do a cast here as well,
so Dim form = CType(menuItem.Tag, and we'll cast that to Form), and then finally we'll activate the form,
so form.Activate. Alright, that completes the code, so let's try this out.
Press F5, and then create some new forms, and then pick one of the windows, and then click the Window menu
option, and there we go, New Document, New Document 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and so on, and if I click any one of these
it gets highlighted or activated; if I delete a couple and then come back over here and now click, you can
see this gets refreshed. So that completes the implementation of our Window menu, and it also completes the
implementation of our SDI application.