chào các bạn , đây là Rob , và cảm ơn các bạn đã chọn xem phần giới thiệu winform
modulm này giới thiều về khóa học , và rồi sẻ học hết 3 chủ đề chính của winform
những ứng dụng , form , controls , và sự kiện
có 2 chú ý trước khi chúng ta thảo luận về winform
những developer xem khóa học này thì đãm bảo sẻ hiểu biết về VB or C# và việc sử dụng
visual stdio , tôi đã đưa ra 1 vài khóa học , bạn có thể sử dụng để đánh bóng những skill nếu bạn cảm thấy
bạn cần thiết để làm vậy
những minh chứng trong khóa học này sẻ là đk hoàn thành trước trong VB
tôi chỉ hiển thị vi dụ về c# , nơi có 1 sự khác biệt quan trọng giữa cái gì thì cần đk
hoàn thành trong c# và cái gì đk hoàn thành trong VB , tuy nhiên những ví dụ code có thể download đã đk hoàn chỉnh trong cả 2 ngôn ngữ
bây h có thể tới khóa học
winform là sự kết hợp những class in .net và những công cụ trong VS mà cho phép bạn
xây dựng ứng dụng form truyền thống , winform là thành phần của .net ngay từ lúc đầu
nhưng sự phát triển thực sự của nó đã kết thúc với .net 3.5 và VS 2008 ( thôi mấy cái giới thiệu ,mình chẳng dịch đâu , lâu la, mất thời gian )
This is in some ways a good thing; as Kate Gregory puts it, Windows Forms is in the "Safe Zone," meaning it's
not continually evolving like many other .NET framework technologies, so the skills you had five years ago
still apply today. But in some ways it's a bad thing, because Windows is evolving, and Windows Forms isn't.
One example of this that we'll see in the course is that there are no controls in Windows Forms that enable
you to add a ribbon to your application. So like any other technology, there are pros and cons to using
Windows Forms, but if you're going to build applications that have tight integration with Windows, I think
Windows Forms is still the most productive way to build those applications.
This course is made up of 10 modules. This module is on Forms, Controls, and Events.
I'll discuss the contents of this module in more detail in just a moment.
The next module has some additional information on Forms and Controls.
Here we'll cover some specifics about the Form lifecycle, the use of dialogs, menus, toolbars, and user controls.
The coverage of these topics is required setup for the next three modules, where we'll build three
applications from start to finish. First we'll build a Multiple Document Interface Application, then we'll
build a Single Document Interface Application, and finally we'll build an Explorer-Style Application.
The next four modules focus on the Data Binding features of Windows Forms and Visual Studio.
We'll see an introduction to Data Binding, we'll take a look at Data Binding to DataSets, Data Binding to a
LINQ to SQL model, and then finally using the DataSources window and the Drag-and-Drop Data Binding features
included in Visual Studio. I'd just like to mention at this point that these four modules cover Data Binding.
Now I will include some material that introduces ADO.NET, and DataSets, and LINQ to SQL, but the focus is on
Data Binding, not the data access technology. The final module in the course covers Deployment options,
with a specific focus on ClickOnce.