Now I want to build the same program we built previously, but this time using the Windows Forms Tools and Designers.
So in Visual Studio, I'll choose File, New, Project, and then in the Windows section, I'll choose the
Windows Forms Application template. I'm going to name my project Designer, and then click OK.
This project template gives us a form by default, and this form has two views; it has the design view, and it
has the code view. I can switch to the code view by right-clicking and saying View Code.
Now, I don't want my class to be named Form1, I want it to be called MyForm, so I'll come over here in the
Solution Explorer, I'll right-click on Form1.vb, and choose Rename, and I'll rename it to MyForm, hit Enter,
and it's saying I'm renaming the file that contains the class definition, do I also want to rename the class,
and I do, so I'll click Yes, and notice now my Class has been renamed to MyForm.
Now I want to set some properties of the form, but instead of doing that in code in the constructor,
I'll come over to the Designer, and I'll click on the form, and then I can set properties over here in
the Properties Window. So, for example, if I want to change the title of the form to MyForm, that's the Text
property, so I'll just change this to MyForm, hit Enter, and notice that that change gets put over here.
And then if I want to resize the form I can come over to size, and instead of 300,300 let's make this 500,430
and hit Enter, and now you can see that my form is resized. With the form properties set, I can now add the
controls to the form, so I'll do that by opening up the Toolbox, and I'll pin the Toolbox open, and now I can
drag and drop the controls from the Toolbox over here onto the form design surface.
So, I want a TextBox, I want a Button, and I want a Label. Once I have the controls on the form, I can unpin
the Toolbox to give me more space here on my Designer, and then I can drag and drop the controls around.
So I want the TextBox to be up here. Now notice as I'm dragging I'm getting these snap lines, the Windows
Forms Designer gives us snap lines so that we can align and resize controls to be similar to each other,
and it also give us snap lines to help us conform to the Windows look and feel guidelines.
So, for example, if I take the button and I move it out below the TextBox, you'll see that I get the left and
right snap lines, but I'll also eventually get a small snap line in between the controls.
So this is saying that these controls meet the standard Windows Forms guidelines in terms of space between
the two controls. Also, if I move the TextBox up here towards the top left, notice there's a snap line here
to the left, and eventually there'll be a snap line near the top. So again, this is indicating that this
control is now positioned using the Windows Forms guidelines in terms of how far the control should be from
the top of the form, and how far it should be away from the left of the form.
Now in this particular case I'm not going to follow the guidelines exactly, because I want the properties of
the controls to be the same as they were in our previous example. So I'll start out with a TextBox,
I'll click on it to make sure it's highlighted, and then come over to the Properties Window; you can see this
dropdown at the top is indicating we're setting properties for the TextBox.
I want the name of the TextBox to be MessageTextBox, so I'll set the Name property.
I want the Left and Top to be both 25, so I'll scroll down here, and notice there's no left, and if you
scroll down to the Ts, there's no top, and by the way, I'm showing these in alphabetical order, I've done
that by clicking the alphabetical option. If you're not seeing them in alphabetical order, you probably
have your properties organized by category. I just find it's easier to find things if you sort them alphabetically.
So anyways, you won't find Left and Top in here, but you will find Location.
And then underneath Location we have X and Y; this is our Left and our Top, so I want these to be both 25,
so I'll set these to 25 and then 25. And then finally, I want the Width to be 200; I won't find a Width
property, but I will find Size, and if I expand that, I can set the Width here to be 200.
Now I can click on my button, I want to set the name to ShowMessageButton; I want to set the Left at 25,
and the Top to 75, so I'll come down to Location, so I want the Left to be 25, and I want the Top to be 75.
I want the Width to be 200, so I'll come down to size and set the Width to 200.
And then finally I want the Text to be ShowMessage. And then finally I'll click on my label, I want the name
of the label to be MessageLabel. I want the Position to be 25 and 125; I believe it is, so I actually can
just set this by the location, so 25,125. And I want the Width to be 200, so I'll just set the Width to 200.
And notice I typed 200 and hit Enter, but nothing changed, and that's because the label actually has a
property called AutoSize, and I want to change that, so I'll come up to AutoSize, set this to False, I want
take explicit control over that, and then now come back to size, and there you can see now my Width is set to 200.
And then finally, I want to set the default Text to be Label in square brackets the way we had it in our previous example.
And now I want to add the event handler for the button, so when I click the button the text from the TextBox
gets put into the label. So over here in our Properties Window, right now we're showing the properties
because this option is selected. If I want to switch to the Events view, I'll click the little lightning
bolt, and now we can see the different events for the button. And if I want to add the event handler for the
Click event, I'll make sure it's selected, and then over here in this space I'll just double-click.
So here's our event handler Sub routine; notice it has the signature we saw before, sender As Object,
e As EventArgs, and it's handling the ShowMessageButton.Click, or the Click event for the ShowMessageButton.
So now if I type in the same code we had before, so MessageLabel.Text = MessageTextBox.Text, and then hit F5,
and then type some text into the TextBox, and then click the button, we can see that the text from the
TextBox gets transferred over to the label. So functionally our application is the same, but the code that
we see for the form is greatly reduced from what we saw earlier. Now all the code we wrote earlier, at least
similar code, is there in the project, it's just not being shown to you or made obvious to you.
We'll explore this further in the next section.