When we compare the code-only version of our Windows Forms project to the one we just created using the
Tools and Designers, it may appear that there's a lot of code missing.
A couple of things that might have jumped out at you, where's the code for the controls to create them and
set their properties? And also where's the start-up code with our main method where we use Application.Run
to kick off an instance of the main form. Let's talk about the controls first.
We added the controls to our program by dragging and dropping them from the Toolbox onto the Design surface,
and then setting their properties and events using the Properties Window.
Well as we were doing this, Visual Studio behind the scenes was generating code to create the variables for
the controls, to instantiate the controls, to set their properties, and to attach their events, and most of
this generated code was going into a file in your project that's actually hidden from you by default.
If you have a form named MyForm, the definition of the MyForm class is in two separate files;
there's MyForm.vb or MyForm.cs, and that's where the code that you write goes, and then there'll also be
MyForm.Designer.vb or MyForm.Designer.cs, and that contains the code that's generated by Visual Studio.
So part of the class is in MyForm.vb, and the other part of the class is in MyForm.Designer.vb.
So this concept of having a single class declaration that spans multiple files is called Partial Classes,
and it's used in this case to ensure there's a clean separation between your code and the designer generated
codes for your forms.
Moving on to the start-up code, if you're writing your Windows Forms application in Visual Basic, this code
is also generated for you. In fact, you get a complete custom Application object that's used instead of the
System.Windows.Forms.ApplicationObject we used in our code-only example.
This custom Application object derives from Microsoft.VisualBasic.WindowsFormsApplicationBase, and is
accessible in your code using My.Application. We can configure the properties and events, including the
start-up form for this custom Application object, using the highlighted section of the Application tab of
the project properties. If you're writing Windows Forms application in C#, the project includes a start-up
class that has the standard main method, and uses the traditional Application.Run that we saw earlier.