Let's review the project we created in the last demo. We have a Form Designer, our Form Designer has the
controls laid out on it. We set the control properties through the Properties Window, and then we added the
event handler for the Click event for the ShowMessageButton over here in our form.
Now when comparing the form class we have here to the one we had when we wrote this program using code only,
the thing that's clearly missing is the declaration in setting the properties of all the controls.
That code actually is in the form class, it's just hidden from you.
So here we have MyForm.vb. Up in the Solution Explorer toolbar, there is an option to Show All Files,
so I'll select that, and then I'll expand MyForm.vb, and you see we have this other file MyForm.Designer.vb.
So if I open this up, notice that this is the declaration for a class or at least a partial class called MyForm.
And then over here, we also have a declaration for a class called MyForm.
This is called a partial class, where we have a single class definition that spans over multiple files;
in this case it's two files. So, in this file, we have the code that's generated by the Designer, so every
time we go and interact with the form, we add controls, we set control properties, we add event handlers,
anything like that, the code in this file changes. And then we have our code, which is this over here.
So there's a clean separation between generated code and our code.
And if you come back over to the designer code here, and scroll down, one thing that's important is you see
there's a comment here; we're not meant to edit this code in the designer file, and in fact that's one of
the reasons why it's hidden from you by default. But down here in this method called InitializeComponent,
we'll see we have the declarations for all our controls, so every time we add a control to the form or remove
it, this code here will change. And notice that each of the controls is declared WithEvents.
And then if we scroll up, we'll find where the controls get instantiated, and then down below here, we have
the setting of the properties for each of the controls, and then down here we have where the controls are
added to the controls collection of the form; and also we have the place where the properties of the form
are set as well. Now, where does the InitializeComponent method get called?
It actually gets called by the constructor of the form, even though you won't see that code anywhere inside of here.
It's actually code that gets generated by Visual Studio, and it's hidden from you.
But, if you go over to your part of the code, and add a constructor, you'll see that it adds in the call to
InitializeComponent for you. So InitializeComponent has to be called by the constructor; if you don't
explicitly do it, it will implicitly get done for you by the code generated by Visual Studio.
If we come over to the C# project, here we can see we have the Designer, and we have our part of the code.
Notice that in the C# version there is a constructor for you and it does call InitializeComponent,
so instead of that being hidden from you, it's explicitly shown. Also, without having to go and Show All
Files, if we expand the MyForm node, we'll see that it shows the Designer.cs file here.
So again, in the C# version this is not hidden from you, but basically the code file works exactly the same thing;
it's a partial definition of the MyForm class, here's the other part over here, the code that you write,
and then in the InitializeComponent, which is in this region right here, we create the controls, we set the
control properties, down here is where we attach the event handler, so again C# only has the dynamic event
handling; VB uses the static and the Designer generates code that uses the static.
And then down here is where we actually have the declaration of our different controls.
Now what about the start-up code? So over here in our C# program, we have this file called Program.cs,
and if we open it up we can see there is our static void Main, and here's where we're calling Application.Run,
passing in a new instance of the form class. We also have a couple of the properties of the Application
object being set here. Now, if we come back to the VB project, there is no program or start-up VB file.
Again this code is being generated for you. So, if we go to the properties for the project by right-clicking
on the project and choosing Properties, we'll see here in the Application tab, there's this Enable
application framework, and then there's the application framework properties here.
And when you modify these properties, you're configuring how the Application object gets generated.
So again with the Show All Files on, if we expand My Project, there'll be a file in here called Application.myapp,
And inside of here, there'll be a file Application.Designer.vb, and if we open that up, and then scroll down,
we can see this declaration of this class called MyApplication. So instead of using the System.Windows.Forms
Application object, the way that C# does and the way that we did in our code-only example, in Visual Basic,
when you use the Windows Forms template, and have the application framework on, again that you Enable
application framework, then this code will get generated for you, and it generates a custom application
object that' used in your application. So effectively, this code is doing what this code does over here in
this C# version. So building a Windows Forms application using the tooling provided by Visual Studio is more
productive, but there's a lot stuff happening behind the scenes that may not be obvious to you.
So hopefully starting out by building a project using code only, then building a project using the Designer,
and then seeing where the Designer puts the code and how things all work together, makes this whole process
a little bit clearer to you.