When building any kind of program using Visual Studio, using its Tools and Designers, there'll be things
that will happen that may not be obvious to you, and there'll be files that are generated that may be
purposely hidden from you. And while these obfuscations are done for a reason, they can impede the learning
of a new technology. So what we're going to do over the next few sections of this module is build a
Windows Forms application just using code. Doing so will ensure that you see and understand each of the
individual pieces of the program and how they fit together. In this section we'll take a look at how to
build a Form and show it on the screen. Creating a Form is a pretty simple process.
We just create a class that inherits from System.Windows.Forms.Form, and set its properties in the constructor.
How we show a Form on the screen will depend on whether we're talking about the start-up form, which is the
form that shows when the application first starts up; this is quite often also called the Main Form.
Well we're talking about a secondary form. This is a form that starts up during the life cycle of the
program, and it will almost always show either beside or on top of the main form.
For secondary forms, we just create an instance of the form type, and then call either the Show() or
ShowDialog() method to display the form. Using Show will display the form modelessly; using ShowDialog will
display the form modally. When starting up a Windows Forms application, a little bit more work needs to be
done than just showing the start-up or main form. This work is done by the Application Object.
So, on start-up, we'll create an instance of our Form object and pass it to the Run method of the Application Object.
This not only displays the main form, but it also tells .NET to listen in on the Windows message loop.
Recall that the .NET framework sits on top of Windows, and it's actually Windows which is getting information
about the user interaction with our program, so the Application Object listens in on the message loop and
then passes the messages Windows is getting off to the actual forms and controls we have in our .NET application.
To close our program we can call Application.Exit; this tells .NET to stop listening on the Windows message
loop and close all open forms. But we normally don't have to explicitly call Application.Exit, because
closing the Main Form by default implicitly calls this method for us.
Okay, that's enough information to get us started, so we can move on to the first part of the demo,
where we'll see how to create the Form class and show it on the screen.