The first step in creating our code-only Windows Forms Application is to create the Visual Studio project.
So over here in Visual Studio, I'll choose File, New, Project, and because I want this to be code-only,
I'm going to use the Empty Project template. I'll name my project Simple, and then click OK.
Now I want to create the class to represent our Windows Form, so I'll right-click on the project, and choose
Add Class, and I'll call the class MyForm. And I want this class to inherit from System.Windows.Forms.Form.
To be able to do that, I need to reference the System.Windows.Forms assembly, so I'll right-click on the
project, choose Add Reference, make sure the Framework section is highlighted, and then scroll down to
System.Windows.Forms, make sure that assembly is checked, and then click OK.
With the assembly reference added, I can now add the line of code to indicate that my class inherits from form,
so Inherits Form, and I'll just use the Ctrl . to add the Import statement for Systems.Windows.Forms.
And then the last thing I need to do to my class is create the constructor, so that's Public Sub New(),
and then inside of here set any properties I want for the form; and right now all that's set is the actual
title of the form so that's the Text property, and I'll set that = "My Form".
So that completes our form class. Now we need to add the main method, which is the entry point for our
Visual Basic application. The main method goes inside of a module, so I'll right-click on the project,
and choose Add Module, I'll call this module Startup, click Add, and then inside the module I'll create the
main method, so that's Public Sub Main(), and now I need to create an instance of my form, so Dim form As New MyForm.
And then, as I mentioned, I can use like form.Show, right there is a show method and show dialog method,
but for the start-up form, which is what this form instance is going to be, we need to instead use
Application; so this is a Singleton object, it lives in the System.Windows.Forms namespace, so again I'll
use Ctrl . to add the Import statement we need, and then the method I want to call is Run, and then pass
in my form object. So again, this does a few things. 1) It starts listening in on the Windows message loop,
2) It sets this form object as the main form for the application, and then 3) It actually shows the form.
So with this code complete, I can now press F5 to run the application, and there is our form.
Just one note for those of you who are following along using C#, if I go over to the C# version of this project,
so, Recent Projects, SimpleCS, and then press F5,
you'll notice we our form, but we also get this console window behind it.
So to alleviate that issue, we'll just go to the project, right-click, choose Properties, and then in the
Application tab, just change the Output type from Console Application to Windows Application, save,
and press F5 again, and now you just get the form showing up.