Now that we have our Form, we'll add some Controls to build the user interface for our program.
We'll be using controls that are built into the .NET framework; I'm not sure exactly how many of these there
are, about 30 to 40 maybe, and for many applications these are the only controls that you'll need.
Now if you do have a need for a control that's not in the .NET framework, there's a very large third-party
market out there, and you could even create your own custom controls.
The properties for controls will differ depending on what the controls do.
But because all controls inherit from System.Windows.Forms.Control, they will share some common properties.
Three of these common properties are related to positioning, and three are related to sizing.
When positioning a control, you can either set the Top and Left properties.
Top is the number of pixels that the top edge of the control is away from the top of the form, and Left is
the number of pixels that the left edge of the control is away from the left edge of the form.
Or you can set the Location property, which is a point which represents both of those values.
Similarly, when you're setting the Size of the control, you can set the Height and Width properties, or you
can set the Size property.
To programmatically add a control to a form takes a few steps. First we'll create a private field for the
control, then in the forms constructor, we'll create an instance of the control and store our reference
to that in the private field, we'll set the properties of the control, and then we'll add the control to the
Controls to the collection of the form. Now let's move back to the demo, where we'll add a few controls to the form
to build the user interface.