So I'm back in my Visual Studio project, and I have the code for the form open, and I want to add three
controls; a TextBox, a button, and a label. And in the next section, we add event handlers, we'll take the
text out of the TextBox and put it into the label when the user clicks the button, but for right now we'll
just actually create the controls. So the first thing I'll do is create a field to represent each of the controls.
Our TextBox will be called the Message TextBox, so that's Private MessageTextBox, and that'll be a TextBox.
Then we'll create our label, which will be called MessageLabel, and finally we'll create the button,
and that'll be ShowmMessageButton. Now down in the constructor, we'll create instances of each of these
controls and add them to the controls collection of the form. So we'll start with a TextBox,
so MessageTextBox = New TextBox, and then we'll add this to the controls collection of the form, so that's
Me., me is a reference to the form, and we want its Controls collection, and we want to Add in MessageTextBox.
Below the TextBox I want the button, so I'll just copy and paste the name of the button here, and we'll say
ShowMessageButton = New Button, and then again we'll add this to the Controls collection.
And then finally, we'll add our label that will be below the button.
(typing)
Now I need to set the properties of each of the controls, so we'll start out with a TextBox, so we'll set
the Left property, so we'll set that = 25. So I want the left edge of the control to be 25 pixels away from
the left edge of the form. I'm also going to set the Top property, and I'll also set that to 25, so the
top of the TextBox will be 25 pixels down from the top of the form, and then I'll also set the Width, and
we'll set that = 200. Then for the button, I'll also set those three properties, Top, Left, and Width.
So, for Left, I want this to be = to 25, so basically I want the TextBox and the button to align on the left side.
I want the button to show below the TextBox, so I set the Top property to a number higher than 25, we'll
increment it by 50, so the top of the button will be 50 pixels below the top of the TextBox.
And then for the Width, we'll just keep it at 200. And then I want to do the same thing for the Label here.
So, the Left is again 25, for the Top we'll go 50 below the top of the button, so that'll be 125, and then
for the Width we'll stay consistent and just set that = 200. So with this code down, we should be able to Run,
so let's hit F5, and now we have our form. What we don't have is any text, so I forgot to add that,
so let's just stop this and come back down here. I want the TextBox to start out being empty.
I want the button to say ShowMessage, so our ShowMessageButton.Text = Show Message.
And when the form first shows I want the text of the label just to be Label, so we could actually see it,
so our MessageLabel.Text = "(Label)" in square brackets. Alright, now let's run again.
Alright, so there's our TextBox, there's our button, and there's our Label.
And again in the next section we'll talk about event handlers, where we'll take the text that's in here and
when we click the button, we'll put it into the label here. Alright, so just to review, we create our
fields to represent each of the controls, we then instantiate the controls here in the constructor,
we set the properties, and then we add the control to the controls collection of the form.