Now that we have a form and we have controls in that form, we can talk about Events and Event Handlers.
Events are raised as the user interacts with the program. For example, they click on a button, they resize
a form, they change a selected item in a list box or a combo box; each of these user interactions causes
one or more events to be raised in the system. And what we can do as developers is write code called
event handlers that run when a specific event is raised. Event handlers are methods with a signature specific
to the kind of event that's being raised. The method is always a Sub routine or a void function, and the
method almost always takes two parameters. The first is of type object, and this is a reference to the
object that raised the event. And the second is of type EventArgs, or something that derives from EventArgs,
and this has information specific to the event. A couple of important things to note that may not be obvious
about event handlers is 1) A single event may have multiple event handlers, and 2) A single event handler
may handle multiple events. For the latter case to work, the two different events must have the same event handler signature.
We'll see an example of this when we build the MDI application later on in the course.
In Visual Basic there are two different ways to attach an event handler to an event.
We can do it statically or we can do it dynamically. To be able to attach an event handler statically,
the variable that represents the control must have been declared using the WithEvents keyword.
If this is the case, then we can add a Handles clause to the end of the signature for the event handler
method, indicating which event or events that this event handler handles.
So taking a look at the code snippet on the slide, you can see that the ShowMessageButton variable has been
declared WithEvents, and then after the parameter list in the ClickEvenHandler Sub routine, we can see that
this event handler handles the Click event of the ShowMessageButton.
When attaching an event handler dynamically, we don't have the requirement that the variable representing
the control was declared WithEvents. If it was, that's fine, but it doesn't have to be.
Then at some point in our code we can use the AddHandler statement to attach the event handler to the event.
The syntax is the AddHandler keyword, then the event we want to handle, and then a pointer to the event handler.
So taking a look at the code snippet, we can see that in the constructor for the form, we're using the
AddHandler statement to indicate that the ClickHandler method is the event handler for the click event of the
ShowMessage button. Notice there is no Handles clause in the signature for ClickHandler; the Handles clause
is only used in static event handling. Now if you've attached an event handler to an event dynamically using
the AddHandler statement, you can later detach that event handler from the event using the RemoveHandler statement.
There is no equivalent to RemoveHandler when you use static event handling.
When working with C#, we can only attach event handlers dynamically; there are no equivalents to WithEvents
and Handles in C#. The way we attach an event handler to an event is using the += operator.
On the left-hand side of the operator we have the event, and then on the right-hand side we have the name
of the event handler. So looking at the code snippet, ShowMessageButton.Click += ClickHandler, is attaching
a ClickHandler event handler to the click event of the ShowMessageButton.
Now that we understand the syntax for event handling, let's move on to the demo where we'll implement an
event handler for our ShowMessageButton.