Back in our Visual Studio project, I have the code for the form open, and what I want to do is add an event
handler for the click event of the ShowMessageButton. And when the user clicks the button, I want to take
the text that's in the TextBox and copy it into the text for the label.
Now as I mentioned in the slides, there are two ways that I can do this.
I can do it statically using the WithEvents and Handles keywords, or I can do it dynamically using AddHandler.
In Visual Basic, most often you're going to see the use of the WithEvents and Handles keywords, so that's
where I'll start out. So over here on the Declaration for our ShowMessageButton, I'm going to add in the
WithEvents keyword, so that says that this button should listen for all of its events, and then down here at
the bottom what I want to do is add in the Sub routine, which will be our event handler, and an indicated
handle as the ClickEvent for the ShowMessageButton. Now virtually all event handlers have a common signature.
The first parameter is of type object, we normally name the parameter sender, and this is a reference to the
object that raised the event. And the second parameter, which we normally e, is of type EventArgs,
or something that derives from EventArgs, and it has information that's specific to the event.
When you're writing event handler in code as we're doing here, it's difficult to remember what kind of
EventArgs each different kind of event takes. Luckily, Visual Studio is going to help us out here.
So if I want to add the Sub routine, which will be the event handler for the Click event of the ShowMessageButton,
what I'll do is go to the left dropdown here at the top of my text editor, and then pick ShowMessageButton,
and then over here in the right dropdown, I'll pick the event I want to handle, in this case it's the Click event.
And then Visual Studio will add in a Sub routine with the appropriate signature and the appropriate Handles
clauses for my event handler. So if we take a look, here you can see I have a Sub routine, it's a Private
Sub routine, the naming convention is the name of the control, so ShowMessageButton_ and then the name of the event.
But we don't have to use this name; we can really name it anything we want.
So just to show you that I'll change this to ClickHandler. Here's the signature I mentioned, so we have
sender As Object, and then e As EventArgs, so for the Click event handler there's no special information that
we need for the event, we're getting the base EventArgs. Then finally, this handles the Click event for the ShowMessageButton.
So when the button gets clicked, I want to copy the text from the TextBox into the label, so that's
MessageLabel.Text, is going to be set to the MessageTexBox.text.
And then just to give a little bit more of a visual indication that the event happened, I'll also add in a
message box here just saying that the button was clicked. So at this point we're ready to test out our work,
so I'll press F5, and then I'll type some text into the TextBox, and click the ShowMessageButton, and there
you can see the text from TextBox has been copied into the label, and then there's a little message box
showing up here. So that's how to handle the event using WithEvents and Handles, now let's take a look at
how we can handle an event using AddHandler. So what I'll do is I'll get rid of this Handles clause,
and also get rid of the underscore there, and then up at the top I'll get rid of the WithEvents keyword.
And then down in the constructor, after we've created our button, I'll dynamically attach our Sub routine,
our event handler Sub routine, to the Click event using AddHandler.
So it's AddHandler, then the event we want to handle, so that's our ShowMessageButton.Click, and then a
pointer to the Sub routine that's going to handle the event, so that's AddressOf and then ClickHandler.
Okay, so now if I press F5, and then again type some text in the TextBox, and click the button, you can see
the text is copied from the TextBox to the label, and then there's our message box.
Now one note about the use of AddHandler is that if you have multiple calls to AddHandler for the same
event, the second one doesn't replace the first one, it adds to the first one.
So now if I Run the program and click the button, our event handler will run two times, because I've attached it twice.
So I'll press F5, type some text into the TextBox, click the button; so there's the first run, and then there
is the second run.
Handling events in C# is similar to what we just saw, but there are some small differences, and it's worth
a quick demo. So here I have my form, and on the form we have a TextBox, a Button, and a Label, and just
like in the previous example, I want to add an event handler for the Click event of the button.
So down here, after I've created the button, what I'll do is say ShowMessageButton.Click, and the equivalent
to AddHandler in C# is actually an operator, it's the += operator, and you notice Visual Studio saying TAB to insert.
So I can use the TAB key to 1) Attach the event handler method, so that's the first TAB, and then 2) Actually
create the void function that will be our event handler, that's the second TAB.
So coming back up here, you can see it says ShowMessageButton.Click += ShowMessageButton_Click; notice the
same naming convention we had before, it's the name of the control _ (underscore) and then the name of the event,
and then down here, we have the void function where we'll put our code, and it'll be the same code we saw
before; it's MessageLabel.Text = MessageTextBox.text. And just like I showed you in the VB example, while
the naming convention is commonly used, we don't have to use it, so I can go ahead and refactor this and
rename this to ClickHandler, then click OK, and this will work exactly the same.
So I press F5, and then type some text into the TextBox, and click the button, and you can see that text has
transferred over to the label. So at this point we've seen all the core pieces of creating a Windows Forms
application, we've created a form, we've added controls to the form, and we've added event handlers to those controls.
But we've done all this using code. In the next section we'll take a look at how we can build the same
application, but this time using the visual designer and tools that Visual Studio makes available for us.