Now that we've seen how to build a simple Windows Forms application using code only, let's take a look at
how we can build the same application using the Windows Forms Tools and Designers.
In this section we'll take a look at the process of building the application, and then in the next section,
we'll take a look behind the scenes, and see some of the things that happen that may not have been
immediately obvious to you. To create a new Windows Forms application using the Designer, we'll create a
new project based on the Windows Forms application template. We'll be given a form by default.
We can drag and drop controls from the Toolbox onto the visual Designer for the form, and then we can set
properties of the form and properties of the controls of the form using the Properties Window.
Then we can create the shells for event handlers Sub routines, and attach them to events using the Events
view in the Properties Windows. And then finally, we can write the code behind the event handlers.