Hi everybody, this is Rob Windsor, and this module, which is part of our Introduction to Windows Forms course,
is on Deployment.
Once you've completed building your application, you need some way to get it out to your clients, and with
Windows Forms you have a few different options. For simple applications that have few external dependencies
you can use XCopy deployment; basically you just take the contents of the bin-debug or bin-release folder,
copy them from your development machine over to the client the machine.
For more complex applications you'll need an installer package, and here you have two options.
You can go with the traditional Windows Installer or MSI; there are a few options in terms of building these;
you can use the Visual Studio setup project if you're using Visual Studio 2010 or earlier.
This project type has been removed in Visual Studio 2012. You can use the Third-party installer Tool,
a limited edition of Install Shield comes with Visual Studio 2010 and 2012, or you can go with something
OpenSource like Windows Installer XML or WiX. The other option for creating an installer package is to
use ClickOnce Deployment, and that's the focus of the remainder of this module.