ClickOnce is a Smart Client deployment technology that was added to the .NET framework in Version 2.
The idea behind ClickOnce is to give developers and administrators a deployment experience similar to that of
web applications, while still enabling a rich client experience for end users.
To install an application deployed by ClickOnce, an end user simply needs to click on a link in a website or
click on a file in a file share, hence the name ClickOnce. As we'll see in the upcoming demo, the reality is
that ClickOnce often turns into click twice, or click three times, or click four times, but when the
ClickOnce deployment package has been signed by a publisher certificate, the installation process is
generally pretty simple and intuitive. One other important aspect of the installation process, users do
not have to have administrative rights on their machine to install applications deployed by ClickOnce.
In the upcoming demos, I'll give you a solid introduction to ClickOnce, and we'll see its core uses from
both the developer and the end user side. We'll see how to publish to and install from both a file share
and a website. We'll talk about the difference between Installed applications and Launched applications,
and we'll see how to do automatic Application Updates. Now ClickOnce is one of those topics we could have
an entire course on, so there are several things I'm not going to be able to cover in this module, but I
do want to make you aware of them so you can do additional research when you start using this technology.
So what's not covered in the upcoming demos is handling Prerequisites, like the installation of the version
of the .NET framework or different component suites, and using the Bootstrapper to handle those prerequisites;
storing files on the end user's machine using Isolated storage; Security and Trust Levels; and the Deployment
API that's included with ClickOnce.