In this demo, I'll use ClickOnce to publish and install the Explorer Style Application we created earlier in the course.
I have the application open here in Visual Studio. I'll go to the project in the Solution Explorer,
right-click, and choose Publish to open up the Publish Wizard. In the first page we'll be asked where we
want to put the files the Wizard is going to generate; by default there's a folder called publish; I want
to change that to a folder I created earlier that's called ExplorerInstall in my Downloads folder.
So I'll click Open, and then click Next. Now we'll be asked how the user will install the application; will
it be from a website, from a file share, or a from a DVD or CD? We're going to be using a file share.
Now if I click Browse, you can see I can choose the exact same folder I chose earlier, which is really what
I want, but if I click Open and then Next, you can see it's telling me I need to use an UNC path.
So I'll click OK, and I'll come over to the folder in Windows Explorer, and earlier I created Share so that
I'd have the UNC path, there's the path here, so let's copy that to the clipboard, click Cancel, come back
to Visual Studio and replace what I have with the UNC path. I'll click Next; now it's going to ask me the
installation mode. Do I want to have this installed, meaning I'm adding a shortcut to the Start Menu,
or do I want it launched where I won't. I'll use the default, which is install.
I'll click Next, and get some information about the install, I'll click Finish, and Visual Studio will build
my application, generate the deployment files, which is what you see here, and then copy them to the path
I indicated in the wizard, which is our ExplorerInstall folder, which we see is in the file path here,
and the UNC path over here. Now let's switch from the developer role to the user role.
I want to install the application on my machine, so I come over to the UNC path, and I double-click on setup.exe.
I get the Security Warning dialog, because the manifests that are included in the deployment files were
signed using a self-signed certificate; Windows doesn't know who the publisher is.
Now if I had a publisher's certificate, I could sign the manifest with that and then Windows would know who
the publisher is, and that either wouldn't show this dialog or it would show the publisher information here.
In this case I know that it's safe to install the application, so I'll click Install, and after a short
delay, here is my Explorer Style Application, and it has the same functionality I had when we ran it from
Visual Studio earlier in the course. Now that I have the application installed, I have two options to run it again.
I can come and double-click on setup.exe, and there's my application, or I can go to the Start Menu,
and the name of the application is Explorer, so just search for that, there it is there, click on Explorer,
and there's my application there. So that's the basic use of ClickOnce.
Next we'll take a look at handling application updates.