In this demo we'll take a look at how to handle application updates when using ClickOnce deployment.
So here in my Visual Studio project, I'll go to the project properties by double-clicking on My Project in
the Solution Explorer, and then I'll go to the Publish tab to see our ClickOnce settings.
So here we see the settings from the Wizard, our publish location, or install location, the fact that we want
to use install mode as opposed to launch mode, but we have the ability to set additional settings using these buttons.
And what we're interested in, in this case, is application updates, so I'll click the Updates button.
So as you can see here, when we used the Publish Wizard, even though it didn't ask us, it automatically
configured the application to check for updates. And it set the application to do that at application startup time.
So when we click the shortcut to the application in the Start Menu, it will go to the server, see if there's
a new version, and if it is it will tell us and ask us if we want to download.
Now the other option is to have the application check in the background after it started up.
So if the user is currently using say Version 1 of the application, and we publish 1.5, the next time the
user starts the application it will start up 1, but in the background it will recognize 1.5 is available,
and then the next time we startup the application, it will indicate there's a new version available.
In our case we want the check to happen at startup, so we'll leave the default settings.
Now I should mention that all of this only applies to installed applications; for launched applications
you're effectively running the setup every single time, so it knows right away whether or not you're running
a new version. So let's close this dialog, go back to our application,
and make a change, and we'll make a very small change but one that we can see; I'll change the background
color of our tree view and our list view. So let's set that to something not too garish, how about Moccasin,
there we go, well that's a little bit too dark, maybe how about Cornsilk, there we go.
Alright, so I'll save that change, come back over to our project properties, and notice that the current
version is 1.0.0.1, so now I'll click Publish Now. So that built the application and updated the deployment
files, and I'll come over to my Start Menu, and I'll search for Explorer, and then click Explorer here,
and there you can see the check, and now you can see it's indicating that there's a new version available.
So when you run the application that little dialog pops up indicating it's communicating with the server,
and then either the application runs or you're notified there's a new version.
So to run the new version I'll click OK to download it and then now you can see we have the new version,
which should be 1.0.0.2, and if we close and come back to our project properties, we can see that that's the case.
One final thing I want to mention before I complete the demo. Earlier I talked about the ability to sign
the deployment manifest; if we want to do that we can do that in the Signing tab here.
As I mentioned it's currently using a self-signed certificate, but we can change that to use our publisher's
certificate if we have one. Alright, so that's handling updates in ClickOnce; next we'll take a look at
publishing to a website instead of a file share.