In this demo we're going to change our ClickOnce deployment configuration to have users install the app
from a website instead of from a file share. So let's review the current configuration.
We're currently deploying to this UNC path, and the currently deployed version is 1.0.0.3, and the next
publish will publish out 1.0.0.4. So now I want to change the Installation Folder to be a website,
I'm going to use this Azure website, so I'll come up and just grab the URL, come over to Visual Studio,
and change the Installation Folder to our website, and I'm going to create a folder underneath the root called install.
Now that I'm having the user install the app from a website, I need to make one additional change.
If we come over to our current installation files, we have the setup.exe, well we're not going to have the
user run setup.exe from a website, so we need a webpage. So what I'll do is come over to Options, and then
in Deployment, I'm going to indicate that the Deployment webpage should be publish.htm, and then click OK.
Now I should note that if I was to go through the Publish Wizard here, and make these changes through here,
I would get exactly the same results; the Installation Folder would've changed, and the publish.htm would
have been setup as the webpage for deployment. Alright, so with these changes made I can now Publish.
This updated our deployment files, and there's our publish.htm, but it hasn't pushed these files up to
the website; I'll use an FTP client to do that.
So I'll come over to my FTP client, I'll just Refresh the files here, and then I'll come over to my root
folder in my website and create a new directory called install, and then I'll copy the files from my
hard drive up to my website via FTP.
The upload is now complete, it took about 1/2 minute, and now I'll come back over to my browser,
and I'll go to my website/install/publish.htm.
So here's our published page; you can see it's saying we're going to install Version 1.0.0.4, and then I'll
click the Install button. Down here at the bottom in Internet Explorer it's asking me if I want to run or
save setup.exe, I'll choose to Run, and now the smart screen filter is going to jump in.
So it recognizes I'm trying to run a setup program from a website, and that that setup.exe is only signed
with a self-signed certificate, so it's really trying to discourage me from running it.
So if I click on Actions here, you can see: Don't run this program, Delete the program, and here you have Run anyway.
And sometimes when this dialog pops up you actually have to click a More Options button, which will be down
here, to be able to even see Run anyway. But in this case again we know this is safe, so I'll click Run anyway.
Then we get the Security Warning dialog we saw before, and now I click Install, and now I have my app,
but installed from the website as opposed to being installed from the file share.
And now I want to do an update to my program, so I'll come back over to Visual Studio, I'll go to the form
designer, and I'll do the same thing we did before, I'll just change the background colors here.
So instead of Cornsilk let's go down to something sort of blue or green, how about AliceBlue, there we go.
And then it will save, we'll come back over to our settings here, we'll Publish.
Now this piece is a little bit confusing, because what Visual Studio has done is open up the browser and
show me the published files, but those are the files we FTP'd up before, they're not the new files, so I'm
just going to close that window, come over to my FTP client here, and Refresh.
And now I just need a copy of the files that have changed; it's not all of them.
So I'm going to copy up publish and Explorer.application, and then under Application Files, I'm just going to
copy up the current version, so that's Version 5, so you can see here we have Version 3 and 4; I just need
to copy up Version 5. Alright, so the new version of our application is now up in the website, I can come back over
to Internet Explorer and Refresh the page, and you can see now it's showing that Version 5 is available,
but I'm not going to Install here, I'm going to run from my Start Menu, so Explorer, and then click Explorer,
and you can see it's recognizing there's a new version, click OK, get the new version, and then here's my
new app, with a beautiful new AliceBlue background.