In this section we'll begin our look at LINQ to SQL. At a high level, LINQ to SQL is a layer that lives
between your application and a SQL Server database. Your application performs operations on LINQ to SQL
and it translates those operations into something that the database understands, and then it takes the
responses coming back from the database and converts those into something that your application understands.
Now when I say your application communicates with LINQ to SQL, what I really mean is it communicates with a
logical model of the data in the database. The logical model is generated by the LINQ to SQL designer;
we'll see the use of the designer in the upcoming demo. The model contains classes that represent the tables
in your database, and it also contains classes that represent the rows in those tables.
One of the ways our application can interact with LINQ to SQL is to perform a query on the object in the model.
LINQ to SQL takes that query and converts it into a Select command on the database.
The database returns a set of rows to LINQ to SQL, and then LINQ to SQL turns those rows into objects of
types from the model. We can also make changes so we can change the property values in the objects that
represent the rows, or we can add or remove items from the objects that represent the tables.
Then we can ask LINQ to SQL to send our changes back to the database, and LINQ to SQL will persist those
changes by issuing the appropriate commands to the database.
In addition to the classes that represent the tables and rows in the database, the LINQ to SQL designer also
generates a class called the DataContext. The DataContext really is the central object when we're working
with LINQ to SQL. Instances of classes that represent the tables come off the DataContext, the method we
call to submit the changes back to the database is off the DataContext, the DataContext manages connections
to the database, it manages change tracking, and much more. There's more to discuss about the DataContext,
but I'm going to reserve that discussion until after we've done the first set of demos, which we'll move to now.