In this demo I'll be creating the LINQ to SQL model we'll be using later on to create the entities to which
we'll be binding. So here's our Visual Studio project, it's the same as it was at the end of the last module,
I haven't made any changes, and the first thing we'll do is come over to Server Explorer and pin that,
and we'll create a Data Connection to the SQL Server database we'll be using.
So I'll right-click on Data Connections and choose Add Connection.
The Add Connection dialog here is the one for SQL Server; if I wanted to connect to a different kind of
database, I could click Change here, and choose the appropriate provider, but I do want to connect to SQL
server, so I'll leave that highlighted, and click OK to come back to this dialog.
I want to connect to the default instance on my local machine, so the server name will be localhost.
I want to use Windows Authentication to authenticate with the database, so I'll leave the default here,
and then in here, I'll select the Northwind database, and click OK.
So now I have a connection to the Northwind database, I can come in here and I can see the Tables, I can see
any Views there are, I can see the Stored Procedures, and so on. Now I'll come over to my project, and I'll
add in the model, so I'll right-click on the project and choose Add-New Item, and then I'll switch to the
Data section and choose LINQ to SQL Classes; and I'll call my model Northwind, and click Add.
Our model is going to be the same simple model we've using all along, so I just want the Categories, drag and
drop that onto my design surface, and I also want the Products. So with the model created I can unpin the
Server Explorer, so you can see we're going to have two entities here, a Category entity and a Products entity.
And you can see it's picked up several things from the database, for example, what are the columns in the two
different tables, it's going to create properties to represent those columns, which ones are keys, the types
of the columns, so if I click here on QuantityPerUnit, we can come in here and we can see it knows it's a string,
and if I click on UnitsInStock, it knows it's a number. And if I want my logical model, which is here, to be
a little bit different than my physical model, which is in the database, I can make some changes using this designer.
I will make two changes. If I leave things as they are, the designer is going to create a class called
Product to represent this entity, and a class called Category to represent this entity.
And this will be a problem because I already have a class called Category and I already have a class called Product.
So I'll just rename these; this will become LinqProduct, and this will become LinqCategory.
So now if I save my model and then come over to here and turn on Show All Files, and then come down under
Northwind.dbml, there'll be a file called Northwind.designer.vb or Northwind.designer.cs, depending on what
language you're using, and this file will contain the classes with methods and properties that are used to
represent the underlying data store. Right, so one of the key classes, as I mentioned in the slides, will be
the DataContext, but the classes that actually represent our data are down farther here, so here is our
LinqCategory class, and you can see it as properties to represent the field values, CategoryID, CategoryName,
Description, and it also has a property for the products; categories and products are related in the database,
so I can use this property to get the products that are related to the current entity.
And if I scroll down here farther, we'll eventually see the products class, there it is LinqProduct,
and there's its properties, and there's its implementation. So that completes the building of the model.
In the next demo we'll add the LinqSource class, have it implement ISource, and then implement the different
methods of the ISource interface.