In this demo we'll create our LinqSource class, implement the Get methods, and then setup our form so we can
bind to the new LinqSource. So I'll start by creating the class, I'll right-click on the project and choose
Add-Class, I'll call this class LinqSource. I want this class to implement the ISource interface,
so Implements ISource, let me get into full screen. Now I want to add a field to represent our DataContext,
so Private _context As New NorthwindDataContext, and now I want to implement our two Get methods, so let me
just move those up to the top. For GetCategories, we'll just return the Categories entity,
so Return _context.LinqCategories. So we have a LinqCategory entity in our model, and the designer
automatically added a LinqCategories collection to the context. So it took the name of the entity and
pluralized it to get the name of the collection. And now for the products, I want to do a query to get all
the products in the category that's been passed in as a parameter, Dim query = From p In _context.LinqProducts
Where p.CategoryID = CategoryId we've been passing as a parameter, I want to Select p, and now I just want
to Return the results of the query. Alright, so now that we have our Get methods, we can go modify the form
to use them, so let me get out of full screen, and then open up the data form, and then go to the SourceComboBox,
and modify its Items, so I want to add a new item, and this one is called LINQ to SQL, and click OK.
And now I want to go into the code for the form, so I'll right-click on the designer and choose View Code,
and go into full screen, and I want to add a field for our LinqSource, so private _linqSource As LinqSource,
and now I want to scroll down to where we set the source, here, and just add in a new Case in our Case statement.
And if this is 2, then I want to create a LinqSource, or check to see is the LinqSource Nothing, and if it
is then I want to set the LinqSource to a New LinqSource, and then I want to set the currentSource = _linqSource.
So because of the way we've implemented our form, that should be all that's required to get the data and
show it on the form, so let's press F5,
and then let's change the source to LINQ to SQL, and then let's change the Category here to Confections,
so there's our Confections, and our Produce, and our Seafood, and there's a Test item from the previous module,
and I can scroll through these guys and get the data for the selected item, so that's working, and then our
last test was to come over to, I believe we've been using Outback Lager, and set the unit price to be 100,
and set the units in stock to be 200, I believe we've done before, and that's just not working; let me try that again.
So 100 and Tab, and it changes back, and then 200 and Tab, and it changes back.
Okay, so that's not working correctly. So let's close the running form,
and then come back to our code. And it's not really obvious, but the problem is here when we set the DataBindings.
So we take a look at the overloads for Add, let me just add a , here, and you can see that the IntelliSense
is saying that the next parameter is formattingEnabled, creates a binding with a specified control property
name, data source, data member, and information about whether formatting is enabled, and to get the data
binding to work properly, or the simple data binding to work properly, we need to set this to True when
we're working with LINQ to SQL, so that needs to be True, that needs to be True, and actually, let me just
copy and paste this and it will be faster, so I need to set that to True, and that to True, and then that
to True, and then that to True. Alright, so now if we press F5, and then go to LINQ to SQL, and then go to
Outback Lager, and then go to units in stock and set that to say 200, and then go to units on order and
set that to 100, and you can see those values are preserving, and then if I come over to Chang and then
Ipoh Coffee, and then come back to Outback Lager, those values are preserved, and if I go to say Produce,
and then to Seafood, and then back to Beverages, and then back to Outback Lager, you can see that those
values are still there. So when you're setting up the simple data binding using LINQ to SQL entities,
you need to make sure you set that fourth parameter to True to get the binding to work correctly.
That completes the implementation of the Get operations. In the next section we'll take a look at
implementing Add, Delete, and Save.