In this section we'll be examining how to Add, Delete, and Save when working with LINQ to SQL.
But before we get to those topics, I want to briefly revisit the DataContext.
To this point in the module we've been using the DataContext in the same way we used the DataSet in the last module,
but the DataContext really isn't designed to be used this way. While the DataSet was designed to be able
to store several changes over long periods of time, the DataContext was built to store changes over short
periods of time or units-of-work. So instead of creating a field for the DataContext and using it at the
class scope, we really should be using it at the methods scope. I'll cover the proper use of the DataContext
in more detail in the demo, but I wanted to touch on it now to setup the code you're going to see in the next two slides.
Inserting rows when working with LINQ to SQL on the surface looks similar to what we saw with the DataSet,
but in reality it's quite a bit different. First we'll create an instance of our entity object on the slide
that's the linqProduct, and then we'll set its properties, and then we'll call the InsertOnSubmit method off
of the entity collection on the slide that's LinqProducts, passing a reference to our newly created entity object.
Now the equivalent code in our DataSet example added the object to the in-memory table, and if we were to
take a look at the contents of the in-memory table we would see our new object.
In the case of LINQ to SQL, the object is just marked as a pending Insert; it doesn't get added into the
entity collection, so until we actually push the Insert down to the database by calling SubmitChanges on
the DataContext, we won't see our new object in the entity collection.
So as you see in the code on the slide, the first thing we do after calling InsertOnSubmit is to actually
submit that change to the database. Now you don't need to submit after every single change; if you have a
logical unit, say for example an invoice, where you'll be inserting and perhaps updating several rows in
several different tables, you can do the SubmitChanges after that logical unit.
Deleting rows in LINQ to SQL is again similar on the surface to what we saw in the DataSet example, but also
again different in the same way we talked about on the Insert slide.
To do the Delete or the Deletes, we'll use a query to find the entity or the entities we want to delete,
and then we'll loop through the results set calling DeleteOnSubmit on the appropriate entity collection.
And then finally we'll call SubmitChanges on the DataContext to push those Deletes down to the SQL Server database.
That's sufficient background on Adding, Deleting, and Saving in LINQ to SQL, to allow us to move back to our demo.
So we'll implement this functionality, and we'll also see the changes required to make proper use of the
DataContext, changing from using it at the class level to using it at the method level.