In this demo we'll implement the Add, Delete, and Save functionality in our LinqSource class, so I'll come
over to LinqSource, and I'll go full screen. We'll start by implementing Save.
In Save I want to call the SubmitChanges method off of our Northwind DataContext object.
I'll do that within a Try Catch in case there's an exception; so in the Try it's _context.SubmitChanges,
and then here, if there's an exception, I'm going to show that out in a MsgBox, and then I'll just re-throw
the Exception, whoops, I don't want the snippet, I just want to call Throw there.
Now let's take a look at Add. Here in AddProduct I've passed product object, but what I really need is a
linqProduct object, that's the entity in our LINQ to SQL model, so I'll create one of those.
Dim linqProduct As New LinqProduct, and then I'll just copy the property values from the product object over
into the linqProduct object. And finally I want to add the linqProduct to the linqProducts collection off of
the DataContext. So that's _context.linqProducts; and I've been saying collection, but really the type is
System.Data.Linq.Table(Of LinqProduct), to be more specific here.
Alright, so context.LinqProducts.Add, and we don't see any Add here.
And actually the method of the table I want to call to add my linqProduct is InsertOnSubmit.
So you can see it says Adds an entity in a pending insert state to this table; and this is actually going to
be important, the difference between Add and InsertOnSubmit here, we'll see this in a second.
Alright, so I want to say InsertOnSubmit, and then I want to pass in our linqProduct.
Alright, so now let's press F5, and let's switch to LINQ to SQL, and then come to Seafood, where we've been
adding our test items. And you can see we have Test 3 and Test 4, so let's add Test 5.
And then just add some text here, and some numeric values here, and then click OK.
Alright, so we don't see Test 5 here. If I switch over to another category, and then come back to Seafood
we still don't see Test 5. But if I save the changes, stop, press F5 again, switch to LINQ to SQL, and then
come back to Seafood, there is Test 5 with the values. So the Add code worked properly, but until we save
the changes back to the database, we saw no evidence of our new item in the UI.
Now if you recall back to when we were binding to objects, we had a similar issue, and we were able to solve
it by instead of inserting the object using the context in this case, to do it through the BindingSource.
So let's just change this to BindingSource.Add(linqProduct). And now let's press F5 and switch to LINQ to
SQL, and then come over to Seafood, and then let's add Test 6, and then I'm just adding some values here,
and then click OK, oh there we go; now we have Test 6 being added, all is good with the world, or sort of,
because if I switch over to Beverages and then come back to Seafood, well we don't get Test 6 back from our query.
But again, if I'm to save here, and then close, and then run again, switch to LINQ to SQL, come back to
Seafood, there is our Test 6.
So to this point in the demo we've been treating the DataContext as if it were a DataSet.
Now DataSets are designed to be an in-memory database; they're designed to have a long life, they're designed
to store several changes, which will later get pushed back to the database.
But the DataContext isn't meant to be used that way. In fact, if we come over to the documentation for the
DataContext, so let me open up my browser here, and then navigate to the documentation, and then scroll down
to the Remarks section, you can see here in the second paragraph it says that, a DataContext instance is
designed to last for one "unit of work" and that generally this is at the method scope or as a member of a
short-lived class. So while the DataContext does track changes in a similar way to the DataSet, it's meant
to track those changes over a short period of time and not a long period of time.
So to use the DataContext in the way that it was designed to be used, we need to make some changes to our application.
Through the magic of video editing, I've made most of the changes we need already; the last thing to do is
just go replace the implementation of LinqSource, so I'll remove the current implementation and replace it
with a new one, and then we can walk through the changes. The first thing to note is that there's no longer
a field for the Northwind DataContext. I'm now creating instances of the Northwind DataContext in each of
the methods, and notice I'm doing this with a Using statement, NorthwindDataContext is disposable, so I want
to ensure that I properly clean up after I'm finished using it. Now the fact that I'm getting the Categories
and getting the Products here in this Using statement actually introduced an issue.
Recall that LINQ uses divert execution. So originally I was just returning the LinqCategories, but when I do
this, LINQ to SQL doesn't actually query the database until I do the data binding, that's when it needs to get the data.
But at that point the Northwind DataContext has been disposed and that's a problem.
So I just modified the code here and down here to call the ToList method; this tells LINQ to take this table
and the results of this query and put them into a generic list; that causes the execution to happen right
then, and then the issue with the DataContext being disposed goes away.
And then coming down to our Add, Delete, and Save, here's our AddProduct, so I create a LinqProduct,
I populate the property values, and then I InsertOnSubmit the way we talked about earlier, but in this case
once this is complete I immediately save the changes to the database.
For Delete, I take the productId that was passed in, I find the LinqProduct object with that ID, and then I
call DeleteOnSubmit on the LinqProducts table to delete it and again I save right away.
And then down below here I created a Private method to save when I know the DataContext, and then I just
change the implementation of the Save on the interface to create the context and then call the Private method.
And then one final change, and this affected all of our data sources, is that I remove the BindingSource as
a parameter to AddProduct and DeleteProduct, and I change the method from a Sub routine to a function that
returns a Boolean. So instead of having our SourceObjects ensure that the UI gets updated after an Add or
Delete, I push that responsibility back to the form. And all I do in AddProduct and DeleteProduct is
indicate whether a rebind is necessary. So in the case of the LinqSource and the ObjectSource, I do need
the UI to rebind, so I return True. In the case of the DataSetSource, the UI will automatically rebind,
so I return False. And then over here in the form code, when I call Add or Delete, I just check to see
whether or not the source has indicated that a rebind is necessary, and if it is, then I just call BindProducts.
Alright, so with these changes complete, I can now press F5, and then switch over to LINQ to SQL,
and then go to our Seafood, and there's our Test items, so let's just delete a couple.
So that worked, and let's delete Test 3, that worked, and then without clicking Save I'm going to stop,
and then press F5 again, and then go to LINQ to SQL, and then go to Seafood, and we see we just have Test 4
and 5, so when I deleted those changes were saved automatically, but the UI was also updated properly.
And now if I go to Add, and we've got Test 6, so let's add 7, and then come in here, let's go 400, 800, and 1200,
and then click OK, so there's Test 7, there's our values. If I go over to Beverages, come back to Seafood
Test 7 is still there. And if I close the app and then press F5, and then switch to LINQ to SQL, and go to
Seafood, there's our Test items still there.