In this demo I want to create the project and the forms for our MDI application.
So in Visual Studio I'll choose File-New-Project, and I'll choose the Windows Forms Application template,
name the project MDI, and then press OK. Now I want the form that's given to us by default to be the main
form, so I'll rename it by right-clicking, choosing Rename, and then renaming it to MainForm, hitting Enter,
and not only do I want to rename the file but I want to rename the class, so I'll press Yes in this dialog.
Alright, so now I'll set the properties of the form. First off we'll resize it and make it a little bit
bigger, and then I want to change the title of the form, that's the Text property, this will be a Text Editor
application, so we'll call this guy our MDI Text Editor. And then the key property in terms of making this
an MDI application is setting the IsMdiContainer property to True on the main form.
So once I do that you'll notice that the background here becomes dark in color.
Alright, so that's our main form, now let's create the child form.
So I'll right-click on the project, choose Add, Windows Form, I'll call the form ChildForm, and click Add.
We'll eventually be setting the title of the form programmatically, but for now we'll just set it to New
Document, so I'll change the Text property.
And because this form will be used to edit each of the documents in our MDI Text Editor, I need a control
that will allow us that text. I'm going to use the RichTextBox control, so I'll open the Toolbox and pin it,
and then I'll grab the RichTextBox control and drag it and drop it onto the form.
Now I want this control to take up the entire space of the form; I can do this in one of two ways.
I can use the smart tag here at the top of the control and then choose Dock in Parent Container, or I could
come over to the Properties Window and find the Dock property, and then set that.
So here I can dock to the top, I can dock to either side of the form, or I can dock to the entire form.
In addition to docking the control, I also want to change the name, so instead of RichTextBox1, we'll call
this our DocumentTextBox. Okay, so we have our ChildForm, we have our MainForm, and now we need a way to
create instances of the ChildForm to go inside of the MainForm. So to do that, I'll add a Menu Control.
So I'll open up the Toolbox, and I will find that it's down here under Menus &amp; Toolbars, I want the MenuStrip,
so I'll drag and drop that on my form. And then I'll scroll over and I'll use the smart tag of the MenuStrip
and I'll choose the Insert standard items. So let me just unpin the Toolbox, and now we can see we have a
File menu with some options, we have an Edit menu with some options, Tools, and Help; we're not going to use
all of these, but for right now the one that we want to implement is the File-New, to create a new instance
of the child document. So I've shown you previously that I can select a control, and then to implement one
of its events come over to the Properties Window, choose the Events view, and then add the event there.
But each control has a default event; it's the event that will happen most often for that control, and if you
want to implement the event handler for the default event, all you need to do is just double-click on the control.
So for a menu option, the most common event you'll want to handle is its Click event.
So by double-clicking on a menu option I now have the event handler for its Click event.
So when I click the File-New menu option, I want to create a new child form, so let's do that.
So I'll put here Dim childForm As New ChildForm. And then I want to indicate that this is an MDI child of
the MainForm, so I'll put childForm.MdiParent = Me; so Me is a reference to the MainForm.
And then finally, I want to show the child form, so that's just childForm.Show.
Alright so that's enough to test out our work, I'll press F5.
There's our MainForm, and then I'll choose File-New, to create a new child document, again File-New,
another new document, File-New, another new document, and so on. And in some of the characteristics of an
MDI Application these child documents can't move outside of the container, so I can't move them outside of
their parent form. When I maximize they maximize in the parent form; if I minimize, they minimize in the
parent form, and so on. So the child form in an MDI Application is really a child of the main form.
So that's the core part of building an MDI Application. In the next few demos we'll flush out the menus,
we'll remove the menu options we don't need and add a few that aren't there now, we'll implement the event
handlers, and we'll add a toolbar.