In this demo we'll add the Window menu to our MDI Text Editor. Alright, before I add the Window menu I'm
going to remove the Help menu, I don't need it for this demo, so I'll click on Help and press Delete.
And I'll also remove the Tools menu, again clicking on Tools and pressing Delete.
And then here I'll add the Window menu, so that's &amp;Window. The ampersand(&amp;) beside the W makes it a quick key,
but basically what that means is I can open up this menu by pressing Alt W.
And then inside the Window menu, I want Cascade, Tile Horizontally, and Tile Vertically.
And notice that the menu designer has given these controls meaningful names, so we have
TileVerticallyToolStripMenuItem, CascadeToolStripMenuItem, WindowToolStripMenuItem, and so on.
Now there's one more property that's related to the Window menu, but it's a property of the MenuStrip,
so I'll click on the MenuStrip, and then I'll scroll down to MdiWindowListItem, and I'll set that to the
WindowToolStripMenuItem. So what that does, is now for the Window menu item, down here below Tile Vertically,
there'll be a list of all of the open child forms, and I can use that to see what the active form is, and also
to switch between active forms. This will all be done for me by the Windows Forms Framework.
Alright, so now let's implement our event handlers. Cascade, Tile Horizontally, and Tile Vertically are all
about arranging the child forms inside of the main form, and there's a method on the form object we can use to
arrange the child forms in the way that we want. So let's double-click on Cascade to add the event handler,
and then I'll use Me; again Me is a reference to the MainForm. So Me.LayoutMdi, and then the parameter is
how I want the child forms organized. So in this case I want to Cascade them.
And I'll copy and paste that, and then we'll go to Tile Horizontally, paste this in, and change Cascade to
TileHorizontal and then TileVertically, paste the code in, then change this to TileVertical.
Now I'll press F5, I'll create a couple of child forms, and then choose Window.
Now first off notice that we have the forms showing here below. When we get to the demo that implements
the File menu, these documents will have unique names, so we can choose between them much more easily.
And then up here I can choose to tile the documents horizontally, so one is on top of the other, I can
choose to tile vertically one beside each other, or I can choose to cascade.
So that's the implementation of the Window menu. In the next section we'll take a look at implementing
the Edit menu.