In this demo we'll implement the Edit menu in our MDI Text Editor.
If we take a look at the Edit menu, I want all of the options that were given to us automatically.
Now if we look at these options, they apply to the text in the currently active child window.
So when I click on one of these, I'll need to get a reference to the form object for the active child
window, and then I'll need to get access to its RichTextBox control, which we called Document TextBox.
Alright, let's implement Undo. The first thing we need to do is get a reference to the active child window,
but there may not be an active child window; maybe you haven't created it yet, or maybe they're all minimized,
so we need to check for that. So If Me.ActiveMdiChild isnot Nothing Then I want to cast the ActiveMdiChild
property to ChildForm to be able to access the RichTextBox, so Dim childForm = CType(Me. ActiveMdiChild,
and I want to cast that to ChildForm). And then I want to access the functionality of the RichTextBox
control, so that's childForm.DocumentTextBox, and then we can take a look and see, does it have an Undo method?
It does. And if we take a look through the IntelliSense, we'll see that it also has Redo, it has Cut,
it has Copy; so basically all the operations we want to perform in our Edit menu are available as methods
on the RichTextBox control. So here we want to do Undo. And then the code for the rest of the methods is
basically just this code calling a different method of the RichTextBox control, so let's implement all of those.
So there's Redo, Cut, Copy, Paste, and SelectAll. So at this point we're ready to test out our work.
So I'll get a full screen and press F5.
And then I'll come over to this browser where I have the Wikipedia page for Windows Forms open, and I'll just
grab this text here, copy to the clipboard, come over, create a new child window, and then choose Edit and
Paste, you can see that that got pasted into there. I can grab patterns &amp; practices, and then do Edit, Cut,
that gets cut, come down here, Edit, Paste, and then I can Select All, and Delete, and so on.
So all the functionality we need for the Edit menu is provided for us by the RichTextBox control.
Now one quick note about the C# version of this program, if I come over to the C# project, you can see here's
the code for our Undo, so check to see is there an ActiveMdiChild? If there is then cast that, here let me
just get into full screen; I want to cast that to childForm, and then I want to use the functionality of
the RichTextBox control to Undo, Redo, Cut, Copy, Paste. But by default, the documentTextBox is not visible
off of the childForm. In C#, when you add a control to the form, so let's come over to our ChildForm,
there's our RichTextBox, the control is declared as private, which means it's internal to the form itself,
and we can't access it outside. So what I needed to do to get the code in the form to work the way it does
in the Visual Basic example is change this from being private to internal, and the way I did that was I went
to the Properties Window for the control and changed the Modifier here.
So initially it was Private, I changed it to Internal. And what that did is in the Designer generated code
down at the bottom, it just changed the visibility modifier on the control object.
So that completes the implementation of the Edit menu. In the next demo we'll implement the File menu.