In this demo we'll implement the File menu for our MDI Text Editor.
Let's take a look at the existing items in the File menu. We won't be doing any printing, so I can remove
this separator, I'll click on it and click Delete, and I'll remove Print, and I'll remove Print Preview.
I also don't need Save As, so we'll delete that. And then I want to add a Close menu option between Open and
Save, so I'll click on this separator, and then right-click and insert a Menu Item, and I'll set the text
here to &amp;Close, and then I'll rename the menu item to close ToolStrip menu item.
We already have an implementation for New, but I want to change it a little bit; I want to make sure that
each of the child forms has a unique name or title. So, I'll add a field, which will be an integer we use
for a counter, so Private _counter As Integer = 0, and then when I create a form I'll use counter as part
of the title for the form. So down here I'll say _counter += 1, and then childForm.Text, that's the title
of the form, is = "New Document" and then the value of the counter.
So if we Run now, and then create a few child documents, you can see they each have a unique name.
And then in the Window menu we can see now we have the different names and we can choose between those.
Alright, so that's the New menu, now let's take a look at the Close menu.
So what I want to do here is close the active window if there is one.
So I'll just grab this If statement, and paste it down here. So If the ActiveMdiChild IsNot Nothing then
I want to call the Close method on the ActiveMdiChild. So that's Me.ActiveMdiChild.Close.
So that closes a child form, and then we also have Exit; Exit closes the main form and any children, but all
we need to do is just say Me.Close, and that will take care of that entire process.
So that takes care of New, Close, and Exit; what we have left are Save and Open, and to implement these we're
going to need to use some dialog boxes, or more specifically, two of the common dialog boxes that come with
the .NET framework. Let's implement Save first. So for Save I want to save the text in the ActiveMdiChild,
so again I need the code to get that; let's just go up here and grab it.
And then I don't need Select All, so if the ActiveMdiChild IsNot Nothing Then I'll cast it to childForm.
Then I need to put up a dialog box asking the user where they want to save the file.
So first I will need to go to full screen, and then add some new lines, and then add the code, Dim dialog
As New SaveFileDialog. And we're working with the RichTextEditor control, so this works with Rich Text
Files, or RTF files, so I'll say dialog.filter = "Rich text files, and then the pipe character, and *.rtf".
So in the FileSave dialog, the filter will be just rich text files. And then we'll also indicate that if the
user doesn't give us an extension on the file name, then we'll automatically set it to RTF; so that's
dialog.AddExtension, and we'll set that = true. And then we'll show the dialog by calling the ShowDialog method;
this returns a result indicating which button in the dialog the user selected, so it will be
Dim result = dialog.ShowDialog. Now we only want to save the file if the user clicks the OK button, so we'll
say here If result = Windows.Forms.DialogResult.OK Then we want to save the file, and we can do that using
a method off of the RichtTextBox control. So that's childForm.DocumentTextBox.SaveFile, and then we want to
save into the file that the user selected in the SaveFile dialog; so that's dialog.FileName.
We also want to change the title of the childForm to the file name, so that's childForm.Text = dialog.FileName.
Alright, to review, check to see if there's an active childForm; if there is, cast it to the childForm type,
create and configure and show the SaveFile dialog. If the user clicks OK, then save the text in the document
to the file the user chose and change the title of the form. Alright, let's give this a try.
So I'll press F5, and then I'll create a new child window, and then I'll put some text into that child window,
and then I'll choose File-Save; there's our SaveFile dialog; notice that the Save type is our filter.
I'll save it to my Downloads folder as Doc2.rtf. And now if we go over to my Downloads folder, there should
be Doc2.rtf, and if I open that up, there we can see the contents of the file.
And the final step in implementing our File menu is to implement the File-Open.
So here we'll use the OpenFile dialog, so Dim dialog As New OpenFileDialog, and again I want to set the
filter, so actually that's just this code right here, and then we want to show the dialog, so that's Dim
result = dialog.ShowDialog. And if the user clicks OK, so If result = Windows.Forms.DialogResult.OK,
then we want to create a new childForm and load up the file the user selected, so that's
Dim childForm As New ChildForm, and then childForm.DocumentTextBox.Loadfile, and that is the file the user
chose in the dialog, so dialog.FileName. And then childForm.Text = also the dialog FileName.
And the childForm.MdiParent is the main form, and then finally childForm.Show.
So now we can press F5, and then choose File-Open, and pick the file we just saved a moment ago, and there's
our file, again the title being the path of the file; if I expand this a little bit we should be able to see
the entire path. So File-New creates new documents, File-Open we just saw, File-Close closes the active
document, Save we saw just a moment ago, and then File-Exit closes the main form, and that in turn, actually
before the main form closes, closes the children. So at this point the implementation of the menu is complete.
The last step is to add the Toolbar, and that will be the next demo.