In this demo we'll add a Toolbar to our MDI Text Editor application.
So in the Designer for the MainForm, I'll open the Toolbox, and then in the Menus &amp; Toolbars section I'll
add a ToolStrip. And then just like I did for the MenuStrip, I'll use the smart tag of the TooStrip to
insert standard items. So there's New, Open, Save, Print, we don't need Print, so I'll right-click on that
and choose Delete. Cut, Copy, and Paste, that's fine, and then we don't have Help, so I'll right-click and
delete that, and then I'll right click on the separator there and delete that.
Now that we have the buttons we want, we can take a look at the Click event handlers, and as you can imagine,
the Click event handler for an item in the Toolbar is going to be the same as the Click event handler for an
item in the Menu. So if I double-click on New here,
and then it's going to grab this and cut it and move it up to the top just above the Click event handler
for the new item in the Menu. So here you see we have NewToolStripMenuItem_Click; this is NewToolStripButton_Click.
The signature of the event handler is the same and then of course we have our Handles clause.
So what we could do is say well we already have the implementation we want for New, so let's just call this method;
so I'll just grab this and paste it here, and then I have the same parameter, so I can just say sender, e.
And that will work, if I hit F5, and then I click New, we get a new document.
But a more elegant way to handle this is to just say that this event handler handles the Click event for
the MenuItem, and it also handles the Click event for the ToolStripButton.
And we can do this because the signature of the event handler, or basically the arguments it takes, are the same.
So now if I hit F5,
and then click the New button, we get exactly the same behavior.
Now I could repeat this process for each of the other existing event handlers for which we have a
ToolStripButton, and that will work fine in our Visual Basic application, but it won't work in our C#
application, because obviously we don't have a Handles clause. So instead I'll use a technique that will
work equally well in both VB and C#.
So I'll switch over to the Designer, and we've already got the New button, so I'll click the Open button,
and then I'll come over to the Properties Window, and I'll switch to the Events view, and then for the Click
event, I'll just choose the existing OpenToolStripMenuItem_Click to be the event handler for that event.
And then I'll come over to Save, and here we'll choose Save, and then Cut, Cut, Copy, Copy, and finally Paste, Paste.
So with the VB application, what that did is just do the same thing I did using the Text Editor, it just
added the extra Handles clause, or the extra option in the Handles clause for the existing event handlers.
In the C# project, that would modify the Designer.cs for the form, attaching the event handlers using the
dynamic event handling. So the last thing to do is test out our work.
Let's press F5, and then use New, that creates a new document; Open will open the document we had before;
Save we can save that off to a different file name; Cut, so let me just select this text and then Cut,
and then type in some next text, then come down, and there's Paste, and we'll assume that the Copy works correctly.
So that completes the implementation of our Toolbar, and it also completes the implementation of our MDI application.