Hi everybody, this is Rob Windsor, and this module, which is part of our Introduction to Windows Forms course,
is on Binding to DataSets.
For this outline to make sense, I need to give you a very brief introduction to DataSets.
DataSets are basically in-memory databases. So traditionally what we'll do is when our form loads,
we'll go to a database, get some data, and put it into the DataSet, then we'll data bind to the DataSet,
and make all of our changes in-memory, and at some point we'll kick off a Save operation, where we take all
of the changes we've made in-memory in the DataSet, and push them back into the underlying database.
With that foundation covered, we can now get back to our outline. We'll begin the module with a little bit
less brief introduction or primer on ADO.NET and DataSets, we'll see how we can populate DataSets from a
database, we'll take a look at how to data bind to DataSets, we'll see how to Add and Remove Rows in a
table in a DataSet, and finally how to save the changes we've made in the DataSet back to the database.