In this section I'll give you a very brief primer to ADO.NET, with a strong focus on DataSets, the object
to which we'll be binding in our demos. ADO.NET is a data access technology that's been in the .NET
framework since the beginning, and it provides easy access to relational data stores.
Some of the classes in ADO.NET are database or provider-specific and some are provider-agnostic.
ADO.NET comes with several providers out-of-the-box. There's SqlClient for use with SQL Server, SqlServerCe
for use with SQL Server Compact edition, EntityClient for use with the Entity Data Model, OleDb for use with
OleDb providers, Odbc for use with ODBC drivers, and OracleClient for use with Oracle databases.
The Microsoft implementation of the OrcaleClient provider has been deprecated in .NET 4.5.
In addition to the providers you get out-of-the-box with ADO.NET, there are several third-party providers;
generally these are developed by the database vendors. Some of the third-party providers that are available
are MySql, Oracle, Progress, DB2, Informix, and SQL Anywhere. For a more complete list of the third-party
providers, see the link on the slide. One of the important things about the providers I've mentioned is that
their types all derive from the same base classes, and they all implement the same interfaces.
So coding against one provider will be very similar to coding against any of the other providers.
The key class in each of the providers is the connection. The connection represents a connection to the
underlying data store. To establish this connection, we need to provide a connection object, a connection string.
This string contains information like the name of the database server we want to connect to, the name of
the database we'll be using, how we're going to authenticate with that database, and so on.
The connection string you use will be specific to the provider that you're targeting.
The connection string shown on the slide will be used in our examples to talk to a SQL Server database.
So our SQL Server instance is sqlexpress on our local machine; we'll be using the Northwind database,
and we'll be using Windows authentication to authenticate with SQL Server.
The key class in terms of the application we're building in our demos is the DataSet.
The DataSet is effectively an in-memory database. The data in the DataSet is stored in DataTables,
those tables are defined by DataColumns, they're related by DataRelations, and we can sort and filter the
data in the DataTables using DataViews. So for the more part the functionality that we think of when we
think of a relational data store is available in a DataSet. Now two key things about the DataSet:
1) It's disconnected from any data store, and 2) It's provider agnostic.
In fact, the DataSet doesn't know and doesn't care where the data it's storing came from; that's the
responsibility of an object called the DataAdapter, which we'll take a look at next.
For each DataTable we have in a DataSet, we'll have an associated DataAdapter, and it's the DataAdapter's
responsibility to get data out of the underlying data store and put it into the associated DataTable, we do
this using the Fill method, and then later to take the changes made to the DataTable and push them back into
the underlying data store, we do this using the DataAdapter's Update method.
To accomplish this task we need to give the DataAdapter four commands it can use in the underlying data store.
The Select command is used when we call Fill to populate the DataTable, and the Insert, Update, and Delete
commands are used when we call Update to push the changes in the DataTable back to the underlying data store.
In the upcoming set of demos, we'll take a look a look at how to create and populate the DataSet and then
how to bind it to the controls in our application. We'll take a look at pushing the changes we made to the
data in the DataSet back to the database in a later set of demos.
To populate the DataSet, we'll create the DataSet object; we'll create a connection object appropriate to
the database we're using; in this case that will be a SqlConnection object.
We'll create the DataAdapter that we'll use to create the DataTable within the DataSet.
To do this we'll need to give the DataAdapter object the Select command we'll use to retrieve the data from the database.
And then finally we'll create the DataTable in the DataSet by using the DataAdapter's Fill command.
We don't need to explicitly call Open and Close on the Connection object when using the Fill method, it does
that for us internally. The process of binding a DataTable to controls in a form is very similar to binding
a collection of objects. Where before we were binding the collection to a data source, we're now binding the DataTable.
And before, where we were specifying the property names on the objects, we're now specifying the column names
on the table. We'll see this in the upcoming set of demos, which we'll move to now.