In this demo I'll walk through some changes I've made to the project from the last module to prepare it to
work with DataSets. 1) I've added a new interface called ISource, and if you notice the methods here are
pretty much the same as the methods we had for our ObjectSource, so I'm going to have multiple data sources;
we'll use objects, in this demo we use DataSets, and in a later demo we'll use LINQ to SQL, and I want the
objects that expose that data to have the same interface. So we take a look at the implementation of
ObjectSource, now it implements the ISource interface. So we can see GetCategories Implements
ISource.GetCategories, GetProducts. For Delete and AddProduct, I changed the implementation.
These methods now take a BindingSource and a product, and you can see in this implementation they're using
the bindingSource.Remove and bindingSource.Add. So in the previous demo this code was in the form, now it's
in the ObjectSource class. And then finally I've added a Save method.
In the case of objects in-memory, there's nothing really to do here, but with the DataSet and later with LINQ
to SQL, we'll need to push the changes made by the user back to underlying data store.
I've also made some changes to the code in the form, so let's take a look at that.
So here is the field that represents our ObjectSource, and I've added a new field called currentSource,
which is of type ISource, so we'll have three different data sources, Objects, DataSet, LINQ to SQL; this
will point to whatever the currentSource is.
In the form, I've now added one value to the Sources dropdown, so if we come over here to its Properties and
take a look at Items, I have Objects, and in this demo we'll be adding DataSet, and in a later demo I'll be
adding LINQ to SQL. So in the Form_Load, I set the selected index of that dropdown to be 0, meaning Object
is the default data source, and then I call this method called SetSource, and then call this method
called BindCategories. So let's take a look at their implementation.
When I change the source, I want to 1) Set the data source, meaning get the instance of the Object, DataSet,
or LINQ to SQL source, and set it as the current source, and then I want to bind the categories, and I want
to bind the products. If I just change the category, I only want to bind the products.
Now here in SetSource, what I'll do is check the SelectedIndex of the SourceComboBox; if it's 0, that's
objects, so I'll check to see if I've already created an objectSource instance; if I haven't I will, and then
I'll set that as the currentSource. In BindCategories I just go get these set of categories from
currentSource and bind those to the categoriesBindingSource, and then in BindProducts, I find the currently
selected category, I go get the products based on the current category from the currentSource, and then
bind that to the productsBindingSource. The remainder of the code is the same as in the previous demo.