We can now go create our DataSet and add the binding support for it, so I'll get out of full screen,
and the first thing I'll do is come over to the Server Explorer here in Visual Studio, and you can see I have
a Data Connection, and if I expand this we can see it's the Northwind database.
Now I added this data connection by right-clicking on Data Connections, choosing Add Connection, choosing
Microsoft SQL Server, clicking Continue, putting the address of my server, which is the current machine,
so it's just localhost, and then under here going and selecting the Northwind database.
So our DataSet will be working with the Categories table or data from the Categories table and the Products table.
Alright, so let's go create our DataSet source class, so I'll right-click on the project and choose Add-Class,
I'll call this the DataSetSource and click Add, and then I want to indicate that this class will implement
the ISource interface. Hit Enter, and it will Sub in all of our methods.
Alright, so right now we'll just implement the methods to Get the data and populate the DataSet, and then
later on in the demo we'll add the implementation of the methods to update.
So I'll start by adding a field for our DataSet, so that will be Private_dataSet As DataSet, and then I'll
add a constructor, and in the constructor we'll create and populate the DataSet, so _dataSet = New DataSet,
and then Dim cn As New sqlconnection, so I'm going to be doing a connection to a SQL database, and let me
see if I can get the IntelliSense to popup here, SqlConnection, I guess I need to add the Using statement for
System.Data.SqlClient, and then what I need here is the connection string to the database.
Now I could hard code it on my application, but what I'm going to do instead is use the application settings in my project.
So let me get out of full screen here and then go to my project Properties, and then go to Settings, and I
want to create a new setting called NorthwindConnection, and it'll be a connection string, and this is
Application wide, and I want the value to be a connection string the way we set it up before.
So, I'll choose SQL Server, click Continue, I'll choose localhost here, and then I'll dropdown and choose
Northwind, and then click OK. So that adds a setting to our project which I can now use over here,
so it's just My.Settings.NorthwindConnection, and what it'll do is that will go read the settings file,
get that value, and use it here, and then later on if I want to change the connection string, I don't have
to recompile the application, I can just go into the Settings file, and we can find that by doing
Show All Files, and then under My Project we have the Settings here, and there is our Settings Designer,
and I believe I could actually open this up as an XML document,
and there you see our NorthwindConnection setting.
Alright, so now that we have the connection, I need to create a DataAdapter, so Dim da As New SqlDataAdapter,
and the command that I want to run is "Select * from categories". Actually, in this case we just need
the CategoryID and the CategoryName, so let's be specific, and that's from Categories.
And then the second parameter is the connection that I'm talking through.
And then finally I want to take the data out of the database and push it into the DataSet, so that's da.fill,
and then the reference to our DataSet, and the name of the table in the DataSet, and that will be Categories.
And then I want to do the same thing for Products, so let me just copy and paste this code here, and let me
just change these names; this will be the categories DataAdapter and this one will be the products DataAdapter,
and then here I want all of the columns from Products, so I will do Select *, and From Products, and the
name of this table in the DataSet will be Products. Alright, so now that we have our DataSet, we can
implement GetCategories and GetProducts. For GetCategories I just want to return the Categories table,
so that's Dim table = _dataSet.Tables, and I want the Categories table, and then it's just Return table.
And then for Products, I want to get the Products table, and I'm ready to return the table, but I don't want
to return all of the rows, I only want to return the rows that are of the current category.
So the way I'll do that here is by setting a row filter on the default view of the table.
So it's table.DefaultView.RowFilter = "CategoryID = "&amp; categoryId we passed in.
So that completes the implementation of the Get part of our DataSet source, now let's go to the form,
and add a data binding support. So I need to add another source to the ComboBox here for the DataSet,
so I'll go to Items and add DataSet. And now we'll go to the code for the form,
and get into full screen. So I need to add a field for the DataSet source, so Private _dataSetSource As
DataSetSource, and then I need to add the ability to get the DataSet source in SetSource, so I'll just
copy this Case statement here. So if the selected index is 1, that's DataSet, and this becomes dataSetSource
and just change that, and that, and that, and then this becomes DataSetSource.
And because we're using the interface, the rest of the code doesn't need to change, so we're ready to test out our work.
And before I run here, let me go into the DataSetSource and put some breakpoints, so I want to put a
breakpoint here for GetCategories and one for GetProducts, just to make sure that we're in this actual
DataSource, because in the UI it might not be obvious. Alright, so now I'll press F5, and we can see here
that I'm not hitting my breakpoint, so I'm in the ObjectDataSource, but if I switch over to the DataSetDataSource,
there we hit GetCategories, we just get out of full screen and continue to run, and there we hit GetProducts,
and then we come back to our UI, and now we're looking at the data from the actual DataSet.
So that completes the implementation of the Get part of our DataSetSource, and showing the data in our form.
I'll end this demo now and will implement the Add, Delete, and Save functionality in the next demo.