In this section we'll take a look at how to Add and Delete rows in a DataTable, and how to Save the changes
made to the data in the DataTable back to the underlying data store.
To add a row to a DataTable, you call the NewRow method on the DataTable object, and this returns you a data row.
At this point the data row is disconnected, meaning it doesn't yet exist in the DataTable.
You then populate the column values in the data row, and then to actually add the row to the table, you call
the Add method on the tables Rows collection, passing in a reference to the data row object.
To Delete a row from a DataTable, we can either use the Delete method on the data row object, or we can call
the Remove method on the rows collection of the DataTable, passing in a reference to the data row we would like to remove.
So the general practice is to use a query or a filter or some other technique to get the row or the set of
rows you want to remove, and then to iterate through that result set using one of the two techniques I just
mentioned to actually remove the rows from the table. Now just a brief aside before we move on, if you're
not familiar to the LINQ query syntax we see here on the slide, this is LINQ to DataSet.
The key for LINQ to DataSet is the AsEnumerable extension method on the DataTable object.
This exposes the data rows that's compatible with the LINQ queries.
Another part of LINQ to DataSet that I'm using is the ability to get column values in a strongly type manner.
So using the generic Field method, I can pass in a type parameter, and internally the Field method will
cast the column value I want into the type I've indicated with the type parameter.
These extensions to DataTable and the associated types are really nice when you're frequently working with DataSets.
Finally we'll take a look at how to save the changes to data in a DataTable back to the underlying data store.
First we'll create a Connection object, then we'll open that connection, then we'll call the Update method
on the DataAdapter that's associated with the DataTable we're updating; this takes a reference to the DataSet
and the name of the DataTable as parameters. Calling Update internally calls the Insert, Update,
and DeleteCommands once for each row that's been added, updated, or deleted.
The Insert, Update, and DeleteCommands are not automatically created when you create the DataAdapter.
So you need to do one of two things, you either need to specify these commands using the InsertCommand,
UpdateCommand, and DeleteCommand properties, or, in many simple scenarios, you can create an instance of
the provider-specific command builder object, passing in a reference to the DataAdapter, and it will build
the Insert, Update, and DeleteCommands for you based on the Select command.
We'll see how this technique is used in the upcoming demo. After calling Update we'll close the connection,
and we also want to call Dispose on the Connection object to indicate to the underlying provider that it can
release any unmanaged resources. Notice that the call to Dispose is in a Finally block in the slide; this is
because we want this call to happen whether we have an exception or not within the Try block.
One final note before we move back to the demo, the Update code we have here will work fine if we're just
updating one table or maybe a few tables that are unrelated. But if you have related tables, for example
you have a Master-Child relationship, then you're going to need to use a little bit more complex update logic
to ensure that the rows in the child table and the parent table are inserted, updated, and deleted in the
proper order; in other words, in a way that doesn't break any referential integrity constraints.
Alright, so now let's move back to our demo, where we'll implement the code we've seen here on the slides.