In this demo we'll implement the functionality to add rows to our DataSet.
So let's come over to our DataSetSource and implement Add, so I'll come down here to AddProduct, let's get
into full screen. The first thing I need to do is get a reference to the Products table, so I'll just grab
that code, and I'm going to need that in Delete as well, so I might as well put it there.
And then to Add, we create a new row for the table, we populate the fields in the row, and then we add that
new row object to the table. So I'll say here Dim row = table.NewRow, so currently this row is detached from
the table, and then to actually add the row, we say table.Rows.Add and then pass in the new row, and then all
we need to do here is populate the properties, so we're being passed in a product As parameter, and most of
the properties we need are there, or most of the field values we need are there.
Now in the database, products have a SupplierID, we're not modeling that in this application, so I'm just
hard-coding that to 1, which is whatever the first Supplier is in the Supplier table, and products have a
ReorderLevel, I'm just setting that = 0. So now we should be able to add a product into our DataSet.
I'll put a breakpoint here, and then let's run,
and let's switch the Source to DataSet, and then click Add,
oh and we get an error. Okay, so it's trying to cast the CategoryToolStripComboBox.SelectedItem to Category
and it's saying you're unable to cast object of type 'System.Data.DataRowView' to type 'Data.Category'.
So why are we getting that? Well, in the object binding example, we were binding category objects to the
CategoryToolStripComboBox, but now we're binding a DataTable, and actually really what we're binding is a
view on the DataTable, so each of the items is of type DataRowView, so we can't cast the DataRowView to a
category, so this code isn't going to work. Alright, so let's get out of the full screen, and let's stop
debugging here, and let's go back into full screen. So what I need to do is replace this code to get the
currently selected category so I can pass that off to the AddProductForm, and the code we want instead that
will work in all the different scenarios is this. So we've set the ValueMember of the CategoryToolStripComboBox
to be the CategoryID, so this will get us the CategoryID, and the category name is the currently selected
text in the CategoryToolStripComboBox, so that will get us the category name, and that will allow us to
construct a category object, and then we can pass that off to the AddProductForm, so that should address that issue.
Alright, so let's put F5 again, and now let's switch to DataSet, and now let's click Add, and we'll call this
guy Text 1, and we'll put some text in here, and some numbers in here, and then click OK, and now we've
hit our breakpoint, so our row should have been added to the table; and to see that we could use the data tip
so if I just get into here, sometimes it's a little bit tricky, there we go, so that little magnifying glass,
I want the DataTable Visualizer, so here is our Products table, and if I scroll down, there's our new row, Test 1.
So SupplerID is 1, CategoryID is 1, QuantityPerUnit, and so on. Now notice that the ProductID is blank;
actually, its actual value is really dbnull. The ProductID is an auto increment field in the database,
so since the object is only in-memory at the moment, we won't know the ID.
Now we're going to implement the Delete functionality next, and we're going to see that not having a
ProductID here is going to be a little bit problematic, but we could implement a fairly simple solution to
address the issue.
And if I get out of full screen here, and then remove the breakpoint and continue running, we can come back
over to our app, and let's add one more item, just so we see this without the actual breakpoint in the middle,
so Test 2, and some values, and 200, and say 50, and 25, and then click OK.
So there's Test 2, there's the values. So that completes the implementation of Add, at least adding rows
to the DataSet. Remember, we just added rows in-memory, so if I was to stop the application and then run
again, and then set the Source to DataSet, you'll notice that those values or those rows aren't there,
because we never persisted them back to the database; we'll be doing that in a bit.
Actually, sorry, I forgot to mention one thing previously. You'll notice how we did a product, and I just
added the row to the table, but it showed up properly in the UI, and if I come back over to ObjectSource
here, and take a look, scroll down, you'll recall we had to add through the bindingSource to get that to work
when we're working just with objects. So the DataSet type actually has the proper notifications to know when
things have been added and removed; we don't have to go through the bindingSource when we're working with a DataSet.