In this demo we'll implement the Delete and Save functionality for our application that data binds to DataSets.
So here we're taking a BindingSource and a product. Okay, we actually don't want a product in this case,
that was fine with the ObjectSource, because you can see here in DeleteProduct we're just removing from
the actual collection of product objects. But here in the DataSet DataSource it would be better if we got
the ProductID, so let's make that change. So I want your ProductID, and that's an Integer, and because this
is part of an interface, we're going to need to make that change not only here, but in ObjectSource, so for
Delete I want this to be a ProductID, and also in our interface declaration, which is ISource, and I want to
change the definition of Delete here. Okay, so coming back to the ObjectSource, now that we're using an
integer for Delete, I need to change the implementation to go find the product with the appropriate ID and
then remove it. But that also means we need to change the implementation of AddProduct, because the product
we're receiving from the AddProduct dialog has the ProductID set to 0, and if we add multiple products
they'll all have the same ID. So to address this issue we need to change the implementations of AddProduct
and DeleteProduct to look like this. So in AddProduct I'll do a LINQ query to find the current maximum
ProductID, and then I'll just set the ProductID for the product coming in to that number +1, and then I'll
add the product in. So that will ensure that each product has its own unique ID, and then in Delete, I can
do the LINQ query to find the product whose ProductID matches the one being passed in here, and then I can
remove that particular product. And coming back to DataSet DataSource, for DeleteProduct, we want to have
the same kind of implementation. So what I'll do is get the Products table, and then I'm going to do a LINQ
to DataSet query, so we're going to go through the rows of the Products table, and if the RowState is not
Deleted, and this is there because sometimes we do LINQ queries or LINQ to DataSet queries, it will complain
if you try to inspect the properties or the field values of deleted rows, but the key thing is this part here
where we go and find the product row whose ProductID field value is = to the productId being passed in here.
Now this syntax may look a little bit odd to you. This is part of the LINQ to DataSet, and it allows you
to get the field values strongly typed. So this returns me a ProductID that's typed as Integer not typed as Object.
And now once I have the row that I want to delete, I can go ahead and just call Delete to delete it out of
the DataTable; again this is just being done in-memory. So now coming back to Add, I have a little bit of
the same issue that I had with the ProductObjects. As I showed you, when I add a new row, the ProductID is null,
and if I add several rows, they'll all be null, and this DeleteProduct isn't going to work.
So what I can do is assign a temporary value to ProductID that will be used with the rows in-memory,
but when I push them back into the database, they'll get the proper auto increment value.
So what I'll do is come up to the top here and create a field of type Integer, so I'll call it nextId, and
that's of type Integer, and I'll set its initial value to Interger.MaxValue, so that's the maximum value
for the integer type. I'm using this very large number so I won't have collisions with numbers that are
generated in the auto increment for the keys. And then I'll come down here and just say _nextId -= 1, so a
decrement by 1, and then here I'll say row("ProductID = _nextId).
So again this value is just temporary, it's only used while the object is in-memory, but again once we get
pushed back to the database, this will be replaced by the actual auto increment value.
Alright, so we have the code for Add, and we have the code for Delete, we just need the code for Save.
Let me paste that in. Let me just pause the demo here for a moment.
After I completed this demo, I realized that there's a small but important change that needs to be made to the Save code.
Instead of just closing the connection, what I really need to do is dispose of the SQL connection object.
I discussed this in the slides and showed the proper implementation for the Save method.
So if you came directly to this demo, I suggest once it's complete you go back and look at the video for the
slides that introduces the demo to see the proper code for the Save method.
So we'll create a new SqlConnection object, passing in the connection string, we'll Open the connection,
and then we'll ask the SQL DataAdapter for products to Update the dataSet, specifically update the Products
table within the DataSet. So productsAdapter is a field in this case, so I just need to go add that field,
so up here I'll say Private _productsAdapter As SqlDataAdapter, and then in here where I was creating a
variable, I'll now use that field. Okay, so let's go ahead and run.
And now I've got build errors.  Do you want to continue, NO. Value of type 'Data.Product' cannot be converted to Integer.
So here in the Delete, I have the same issue I had with the Add, where I'm expecting the items in the
ProductsListBox to be Products, but they're going to be DataRowViews, but what I really want here now
because I've made the change to the ProductID, so let's just change that, so this will be the
ProductsListBox.SelectedValue. And then this now will be productId, and then all I need to do is come up
here in my form, right up here, and say that the ProductsListBox.ValueMember = "ProductID" and I just need
to move the setting of the DataSource down here below where I set the ValueMember.
And changing this code reminds me that I need to do one more step, because I forgot to do this when I was
testing earlier, I need to implement the Save button Click event handler,
so this is just _currentSource.Save. Alright, so let's try this again, F5, and then switch to DataSet,
and pick a different category, how about seafood, and then click Add, so let's add in Test 1 and some values
in here, 100, 0, 0, click OK, and then Save. And we're getting an error: Update requires a valid
InsertCommand when passed DataRow collection with new rows. Okay, so what it's saying is that there is no
InsertCommand, and if we take a look at the productsAdapter, and then come down here, let's see InsertCommand
is Nothing, there should also be an UpdateCommand, that's Nothing, and there should be a DeleteCommand,
that's Nothing, but the SelectCommand has our query; actually if we take a look at the text, there we go,
"Select * From Products". Okay, so let me get out of debugging here, and let's come back up to the top.
So for our productsAdapter I've defined the Select command, but to be able to do updates I also need to
define the Insert, Update, and DeleteCommands. So as I showed you, there are properties, so I could say
productsAdapter.InsertCommand, and then I could manually add the InsertCommand, I could do the same Update,
and I could do the same for Delete. Now since we're only updating rows in one table, I don't really need
any kind of complex commands here, so I can actually let ADO write the commands for me, and I can do that
by using a SQL command builder, so I can say Dim builder As New SqlCommandBuilder, and then just pass in my
data, actually it's my products DataAdapter, to the constructor. And what this will do is this object,
once past the DataAdapter, will create the Insert, Update, and DeleteCommands based on the SelectCommand.
Alright, now let's run again, and I'm going to put a breakpoint right here, so F5,
and then go to DataSet, and then here's F5 to continue on, and let's go to seafood, again F5, and then let's
click Add, and test, whoops, I've got Caps Lock on here, Test 1, and some values here, and say 100, 0, and 0,
and 0, and click OK, so there's Test 1. And then let's go to beverages, F5, and then come back to seafood
here and now let's use the DataSet Visualizer, so we scroll down, so there's our item, but now we have the
very large integer value as our temporary key. Alright, so let me close, get out of full screen,
and continue running, and then now save, to that save completed, stop the program,
press F5 again, go to DataSet,
Continue, and then go to seafood, and now let's take a look at the table, and then scroll down to the bottom,
so there's Test 1, but there's the auto generated ID. Alright, so let's close out of this,
remove the breakpoint, Continue running, and now let's Add another item, this will be Test 2, and then
finally one more item, this will be Test 3, click OK. So Test 1 is in the database, Test 2 and Test 3 are
just in memory. So I'll go to Test 2 and click Delete, so you can see we can properly delete items that are
just in memory or have been added since the last save, and then I can delete Test 1, and then finally I can
save, and if I stop and come back we should just have Test 3.
So stop, run again, switch to DataSet, go to seafood, and there is Test 3.
So that completes the implementation of our data binding using the DataSet as a DataSource.
Next we'll look at data binding using LINQ to SQL object as a DataSource.