In this section we'll take a look at the basics of data binding. The concept of data binding is pretty simple.
In our system we have objects that contain data, and we have forms with controls where we want to display
and update that data. Now instead of a developer having to go and take the values out of the objects and
push them into the controls, and then later take the changes made by the user and push them from the controls
back into the objects, we could instead bind the object to the control and let Windows Forms do that work for us.
Taking a look at the slide, I have two objects, Categories and Products; Categories is a collection of
category objects, and Products is a collection of product objects.
And then in the form in the top left, I have a ComboBox where I want to show the names of all the categories.
So I can bind the Categories object to the ComboBox, and then indicate that I want to show the category name
property of each of the categories in the control. Then I can add an event handler to the ComboBox so that
when the user selects a category, I'll go to the products collection and do a query to find all the products
from that category, and then I combine the results of that query to the ListBox.
Again I would need to indicate that it's the product name property that I want to show in the ListBox.
I can also bind the results of the query to the TextBoxes. So here I'd indicate in the first TextBox that
I want to bind the product name, in the second the unit price, and in the third the units in stock.
Now obviously I can't show multiple values and TextBoxes, so the values that will be shown are for the
currently selected item within the collection. So since I've bound the results of the query to both the
ListBox and the TextBoxes, as the user scrolls through the items in the ListBox, the values in the
TextBoxes will change to be the properties of the currently selected item.
What I've described so far is called one-way data binding, where we can take the properties of objects and
show them in controls using the data binding mechanism. But the Windows Forms data binding mechanism also
supports moving the other way; in other words, it supports two-way data binding.
So as the user does data entry in the forms, the changes he or she makes are automatically pushed back into
the source object. So again, looking at the slide, if the user were to change the product name, the unit
price, or the units in stock, then as they Tab out of the control, the new value will automatically get
pushed back into the appropriate property for the currently selected product item.
Now let's take a look at the code we'll use to bind objects to controls.
We use different code depending on whether we're binding to objects that show a single value, like a TextBox,
a label, or a checkbox, or whether we're binding to objects that show multiple values, like a ComboBox,
ListBox, or data grid view. To bind to a control that shows a single value, we'll use the Add method of the
data binding's property of the control. This method has several overloads, but we need to provide three
pieces of information. One is the name of the property on the control to which we're binding, two is the
name of the object, and three is the name of the property of the object, which will populate the designated
property of the control. So taking a look at the code on the slide, I'm binding the ProductName property
of the product object to the Text property of the NameTextBox. I'm binding the UnitPrice property of the
product object to the Text property of the PriceTextBox, and I'm binding the Discontinued property of the
product object to the Checked property of the DiscontinuedCheckBox.
To bind an object to a control that shows multiple values, we set the DataSource property of the control to the object.
This object must implement the IList or IListSource interface, arrays, collections, and the different data
objects we'll find in things like ADO, LINQ, Entity Framework, all implement these interfaces.
Now if we're binding to a data grid view, we're done, because the data grid view shows all of the properties
of each of the objects in the collection. But if we're binding to a control like a ComboBox or a ListBox,
we need to indicate which property we want to show in those controls; we do this by setting the DisplayMember
property of the control. Alright, so that's enough background, let's move on to the demo where we'll
implement the different bits of code we've seen here on the slides.