In this demo I'll prepare the project we'll be using as we begin our examination of data binding.
So here I have the project we'll be using, I named it Data, I renamed the form we were given to DataForm,
I resized the form and set the title. I added two classes to represent the objects to which we'll be binding;
one is called Category, it has two properties and a constructor to set those properties; a class called
Product that has seven or eight properties and a constructor to set those properties; and then finally
a class called ObjectSource. ObjectSource has two fields, one is a collection of category objects, and the
other is a collection of product objects, and then in the constructor for ObjectSource, we populate those two collections.
ObjectSource also has two methods, one to get the collection of categories; in this case we just return the
entire collection, and the other is to get a collection of products.
This method takes a CategoryId as a parameter and then we do a LINQ query to get the products from that
category and we return the result of that query. So in our form we'll be using the result from the
GetCategories method call and the GetProducts method call as the data source for our controls.
We're now ready to start working on our form,
so I'll come over to the Form Designer and open the Toolbox. The first control I want to add is a ToolStrip,
so I'll come down to Menus &amp; Toolbars and add a ToolStrip, and then I also want to add a TabControl,
that's in the Containers section. We're going to have two views of our data, a form view and a grid view,
I'll use a TabPage for each of these. I want the tab control to be docked in the remaining space in the form,
so I'll come up to its Dock property and set that to dock to the rest of the form, and then I'll click in the
TabPage here for the first page, and set its caption to be Form, and then I'll switch to the second TabPage,
and then click its page designer, and set its caption to be Grid.
And then in the second page I'll go to the Data tab and dropdown a DataGridView control.
And then I'll have this dock in the TabPage. I'll also rename the control to ProductsDataGridView.
That completes the preparation of the project. In the next demo we'll start a look at data binding;
specifically we'll look at complex data binding.