In this demo we'll take a look at complex data binding; specifically we'll be binding our category and
products data to a ComboBox and to a ListBox. I'll start by adding a ComboBox; we'll use this to show the
names of all the categories, so ComboBox, and I'll put that up here, make that a little bit bigger, I'll set
the Name property to CategoriesComboBox, and I'll set the DropDownStyle to DropDownList.
The default style is to act as a ComboBox where you can show a list of items, but you can also type in your
own values in the TextBox. By setting the DropDownStyle to DropDownList, we only see the items we add
through the data binding. Now we'll add the event handler for the Form_Load event, and we'll populate the ComboBox.
So I'm going to have a field here, we'll call this guy _source, and that will be a New ObjectSource, and then
here in the Form_Load, we'll set the DataSource property of the ComboBox, so that's
CategoriesComboBox.DataSource = _source.GetCategories. And then I want to indicate that it's the Category
name property I want to show in the ComboBox, so we set the DisplayMember property, so that's
CategoriesComboBox.DisplayMember = "CategoryName". And at this point if I hit F5, there's our ComboBox,
and there are our category names. Following the scenario I laid out in the slides, we now want to add a
ListBox to our form, so we'll add a ListBox, and I'll put that underneath our ComboBox, and I'll call this
the ProductsListBox, and then I'll add the SelectedIndexChanged event handler for our ComboBox,
and then when the user selects a category, I want to go get the products that are in that category, and bind
them into the ListBox. So the first thing I need is the category ID, so that's Dim catId =, and what I
really want to do is get the category ID associated with the category that the user selected.
Now the CategoriesComboBox does have a property called SelectedItem, so I could use that to get the
category object associated with the SelectedItem in the category dropdown.
But the CategoriesComboBox also has this property called SelectedValue, and I'm going to use that instead.
So up here in the Form_Load, I've set the DisplayMember to indicate which properties show in the ComboBox.
The ComboBox also has a property called ValueMember, so I can say here CategoriesComboBox.ValueMember = "CategoryID".
And then now when I ask for the selected value, that should give me back the CategoryID associated with the
currently selected item. Once I have the selected CategoryID, I can then go get the products for that
category and bind them to the ProductsListBox.DataSource = _source, that's our object data source, .GetProducts,
and then pass in the catId. And then finally I need to tell the ProductsListBox that the property I want to
show is the product name, so that's ProductsListBox.DisplayMember = "Product Name".
Alright, so now I can hit F5, and I get an InvalidCastException; Conversion from type 'Category' to type
'Integer' is not valid. Okay, so if I hover over SelectedValue here, we can see that what it's giving me
back is actually the category object, and if I expand that, we can see there's the CategoryID and the
CategoryName; but that's not what I wanted, I wanted the CategoryID.
So let me stop debugging and fix that issue. It turns out that to get the SelectedValue property to work
right, you need to set the ValueMemberProperty before you set the DataSource on the ComboBox.
So if we just take this line and move it down here, and then press F5, this will work as expected.
I'm not sure why you have to set the ValueMember first before you set the DataSource; it just works that way,
but now we can see we're showing the products that are beverages, and then I can show condiments, and I
can show meat and poultry, and so on.