Now I want to complete the scenario we discussed in the slides by adding in three TextBoxes; one to show the
currently selected product name, one to show the unit price, and one to show the units in stock.
So I'll get out of full screen and come over to my form designer, and then just paste in those TextBoxes,
so I have Name TextBox, Price TextBox, and Stock TextBox, and then I'll come back over to our code,
and I'll add in the code to bind those controls here. Now I'm going to bind them to the same DataSource
as the ListBox, so I'll created a variable for that, so Dim products = to the result of our query, and then
I'll bind the products to the ListBox, and then down here I'll create a binding for our NameTextBox,
so that's NameTextBox.DataBindings.Add. I want to bind to the Text property of the TextBox; the object I'll
be binding is the products object, and the name of the property of the product I'll be binding is ProductName.
And I'll do the same thing for the price and units in stock TextBoxes, so I'll just copy and paste this twice
and this will be the PriceTextBox, and this will be the StockTextBox, and the property name here will be
UnitPrice, and the property name here will be UnitsInStock. So now if I press F5, we'll see that we see the
beverages, and as I select different items here in the ListBox, we'll see the properties for that item
show in the TextBoxes. So because I've bound the ListBox and the TextBoxes to the same DataSource,
the underlying pointer to the current item will be the same for all the controls.
Now I will have a problem if I go and change the category here; you can see that I'm getting an error,
and it says "This causes two bindings in the collection to bind to the same property."
So to address this issue I need to clear the binding first before I add it, so let me just get out of the
debug mode here, and then come back down to our code, and I can say NameTextBox.DataBindings.Clear.
And then I can do the same thing for the PriceTextBox and the StockTextBox, so let me just grab this, and do
that, and then do that, and change this to PriceTextBox, and change this to StockTextBox.
Alright, so now I'll press F5, and now I can change the category, and you can see we get the proper behavior.
So the final thing to examine on our form is the second part of the two-way data binding.
So if I come back to beverages, and then pick one of the items, let's pick Outback Lager, and then change
these two values from 15 to be 100 and then 200, and then go to say produce, go through those items, and then
come back to beverages and go back to Outback Lager, there we can see 100 and 200.
So because those TextBoxes are bound to the unit price and the units in stock property of the object in- memory,
once I change the value and Tab out of the TextBox, those changes get propagated back into the object.
Now these are just objects in memory, so if I stop running and then run again, and then go back to
Outback Lager, you'll see we have the original values. But in the next few sections of this module, we'll be
working with data from a SQL Server database, and we'll see how we can push those changes, not only to
objects in memory but back out to the underlying data store.