In this demo we'll add Add and Delete functionality to our project that data binds to objects and memory.
But before I get to that topic, let me review some of the changes I've made to the project.
You'll notice I've added several controls here in the ToolStrip; right now the only control that's being used
is this dropdown, which replaces the category dropdown that was here on the form earlier.
I've also added a few controls, some labels, some TextBoxes, and a checkbox to more completely show the
information for the currently selected product. And then taking a look at
the code behind, I've changed the code here to bind the categories to now bind to the ComboBox that's in the
ToolStrip; I've added the additional binding code to bind to the new controls that I have that show
the product information. And also, when I bind the ListBox, I'm also binding the grid view or the data grid
view control that's on the second tab of our tab control. So if I get out of full screen, and run the
application, you'll see now my dropdown here has the categories. As I change the categories, the information
in the ListBox still changes, and then as I scroll through the items in the ListBox, the information over
here about the currently selected product also changes. And then finally now,
our grid is bound here on the second tab.
We'll begin the implementation of the Add and Delete functionality in our ObjectSource class.
I want to have two methods, one to add a product and one to delete a product, and since we're just working
with a collection here, that's pretty simple, the collection provides the functionality we need.
So DeleteProduct just removes the product from the collection, AddProduct adds it.
And now we can come back to our form and implement these two event handlers here, or the event handlers for
these two buttons in the Toolbar, I'll start with Add. When the user clicks the Add button, I want to show
the Add Product form, which I added to the project. It's a simple dialog form; it has some TextBoxes and a
checkbox so the user can enter the information about a new product; there's no data binding going on here.
And I have an OK and Cancel button, this is the form's accept button, this is the form's Cancel button,
and both of these buttons have been setup to return the appropriate dialog result.
In the code behind for the form,
I take a category As a constructor, so this is the currently selected category, and I use that to show the
category name in this read-only TextBox. I'll also need the category Id later, so I store that category
object in a private field. And then to get the product information that the user entered, I have this
property called Product. I create a new product based on the information in the user interface, and just
return that to the caller. So coming back to the event handler, the first thing I want to do is get the
currently selected category, so that's Dim category = CategoryToolStripComboBox.SelectedItem; it actually
let me type this, so I'll do a cast and I'll cast that to a category.
Then I'll create my dialog and show it, so Dim form As New AddProductForm, passing in category, and then
Dim result = form.ShowDialog. And then If result = OK, then I want to add the product to the products collection,
so that's _source.AddProduct passing in the product property of the form.
And now we can implement the Delete event handler, so I'll come back up here and double-click on Delete,
and here I want to get the selected product from the ListBox,
so Dim product = CType(ProductsListBox.SelectedItem), I'm going to cast out to a product and then I want to
call _source.DeleteProduct, passing in the product. Alright, so now we can test out our work, so I'll get
out of full screen and I'll press F5, and then I'll pick, how about, Ipoh Coffee here, and I'll Delete,
and then I'll pick Sasquatch Ale, and Delete. So notice nothing changed here, but if I force a rebind by
changing the category, and then coming back to beverages, you'll notice that those two products aren't there.
So the products were deleted from the collection, but the UI wasn't automatically updated to reflect those changes.
Also if I add, so let's add, we'll call this guy Test, and the quantity per unit is just some text, and the
unit price is 100, and the units on order is 10, and the units in stock is 20, and then click OK, again we
don't see any changes here, but if I switch the category and then switch back, now we see the change there.
So basically in the Add/Delete situation, the IList interface isn't providing the notifications needed for
the UI to be able to update properly. Another piece of functionality we commonly want is the ability to
navigate through this set of data. Now I can do this by using the ListBox here, just by selecting different
items, but in a way that's kind of cheating, because it's the Click event on the ListBox that's changing
the underlying pointer. What would happen if I only had these TextBoxes?
I have really no way to navigate through the data set. So now let's introduce the use of the BindingSources
and see how we can get this functionality with minimal changes.