In this section we'll take a look at the BindingSource control. The use of the BindingSource is an easy
way to add functionality that you don't get when you bind directly to sets of objects.
The BindingSource enables you to navigate through your collections, sort and filter them, add and delete
items from them, all the while providing event notifications to the user interface so it stays in sync with
the underlying data. To get this functionality, you just need to put the BindingSource between the object
that contains the data and the controls to which you'll be binding.
So taking a look at the code on the slide, I create a new list of product objects and populate it, then I
create a new BindingSource. I set the DataSource of the BindingSource to be the products collection,
and then I data bind the controls to the BindingSource. Internally the BindingSource takes the collection,
which implements the IList interface and wraps it in an implementation of IBinding list.
And IBinding list has the properties and methods that are required to add the functionality I mentioned earlier.
So in the upcoming demos we'll modify our projects to use BindingSources for our category and product data.