In this demo we'll take a look at working with BindingSources. So let's come over to the code behind for our form,
and go to the full screen, and I'll add the two fields to represent our two BindingSources, one for
categories and then one for products. And then here in the Form_Load, I'll say that the
categoriesBindingSource.DataSource = _source.GetCategories. So I set the DataSource here, and then I set the
DataSource for the control to be the BindingSource. So the BindingSource is an intermediary between the
object that contains the data and the control that's going to show and interact with the data.
And then for the product's BindingSource I'm going to use all this code, but I can actually move it out of
this event handler up into the Form_Load, so let me do that, and then here I can say that the DataSource for
the GridView is the productsBindingSource, the DataSource for the ListBox is also the productsBindingSource,
and the DataSource for all these controls is the productsBindingSource.
And because now I'm only defining these bindings once, I don't need to do the clear that I had in the event
handler, so I can get rid of all of these. And then the last change I need to do is down here in the
Category Click, instead of binding products here, I'm actually going to set the DataSource for
the productsBindinSource. So productsBindingSource.DataSource = _source.GetProducts, and the change to the
DataSource for the productsBindingSource here will be reflected in all of our bindings that we've defined here.
Alright, so let's go ahead and test out our work, so I'll get out of full screen and press F5.
So the first thing to check is if I can go and change the category, that works; if I scroll through these,
you can see we're getting the data for the selected product over here; if I go back to beverages and choose
Outback Lager and make the changes we've seen before, so this is 100 and that's 200, and then scroll around
and come back to Outback Lager, those changes are there, and they're also shown in the grid.
So all that previous functionality is working. Now let's go to Steeleye Stout and Delete, oh that didn't
delete, okay, why didn't it delete? Oh, I know why. I forgot to make two changes.
So let's come back to our form. I'm still removing and adding the products using the methods I added to the
ObjectSource class. So the appropriate notifications still aren't being given to the UI, but if I add the
product and delete the product using the BindingSource they will be.
So, let's comment out this line, and then here say _productsBindingSource.Add, so I'll do the add through
here, and it still takes a product, so the parameter will be form.Product, and then if I comment out this
line here and then come back and say _productsBindingSource.Remove, and then again this takes a product
reference, so I'll pass that in. So what these calls will do is add or remove the product from the
underlying collection, but also do the notification to the UI so that it updates properly.
So let's run again,
and then go pick Steeleye Stout and click Delete, and there it's gone, and then pick the last item,
which I can't pronounce, and click Delete, and there you can see it's gone as well.
And then let's just go to another category, how about produce, and click Add, here's our Add dialog,
so Test, and then some text, and then 100 and 100 and 50, and then click OK, and now you can see that Test
item has been added and there are its property values. So now by adding and deleting through the BindingSource,
we're getting the proper notifications and we're getting the expected behavior in our UI.
I mentioned we could also do navigation through the BindingSource, so let's implement our forward and back buttons.
So I'll come back to the Form Designer, and add the Click Event handler for Back, and this is just
_productsBindingSource.MovePrevious, and then over here Forward, and again it's _productsBindingSource.MoveNext.
And now hit F5, and then you can see that I'm able to now easily navigate through my items using these Toolbar buttons.
There's just one last item before we move on; it's not related to BindingSources but is important.
You may have noticed when I add an item here, that as I Tab through the TextBoxes, one we're tabbing into
beverages, which is read-only, which doesn't really help us because we're not going to change that value,
and then two, I'm going from unit price to units on order, and then back to unit stock.
So this is called the Tab Order of the form, and we can control that.
So if I go into the AddProductForm Designer, and take a look at any one of the controls, one of the
properties is TabIndex and another is TabStop. So when I press the Tab key on any control, Windows Forms
will go to the control with the next highest TabIndex whose TabStop is set to True.
So an easy way to set the TabIndex on all the controls is go to the View menu and choose Tab Order.
And you can just click on the controls in the order you want the tabbing.
So I can click this label and then this TextBox, and this guy, and this guy, and this guy, and this guy;
just keep going through them sequentially there, and once I've finished, View-Tab Order.
And then for the ReadOnly control, I'll just click on that and set TabStop = False.
So now when I run my program and click Add, you'll see that I start with Name, because it has the lowest tab
order where TabStop is equal to True, and if I Tab, the next one is quantity per unit, because we set TabStop
equal to False here, and then Tab, Tab, Tab, Tab, to the OK button, and then Tab to the Cancel button.
So when you're building your data entry forms, make sure you set the Tab Order so it's intuitive to your user.
That completes this demo on BindingSources. In the next section we'll take a look at working with database
data and working with data sets.