The demos of this module don't require a lot of setup; the Explorer-Style interface is familiar to anybody
who has used Windows, so all I have is a little bit of guidance. The first is to spend some time and
consider if this is really the best layout for your application, and if you determine it is, then spend
some more time and think about how you want to present information to the user on the right-hand pane of the application.
I see a lot of people use the Explorer-Style interface where it really doesn't fit, and using these
applications quite often felt like the proverbial square peg in a round hole.
Also, if you do feel that this layout is suitable for your application, don't assume you have to use a list
view on the right-hand side. In a lot of scenarios, a user control is a better choice.
Now in our application we're going to build a file explorer, so the list view is a perfect choice for the
right-hand side of the application.