In this demo I want to create the project and setup the main form for our Explorer-Style application.
So in Visual Studio I'll choose File-New-Project, and then I'll choose the Windows Forms Application template,
and I'll call the project Explorer. Click OK, and then rename the name form from Form1 to ExplorerForm.
And then I'll set the title to the main form to be Explorer-Style Application, and I'll resize the main form
to take up most of the design area. Eventually I'm going to need a ToolStrip, so let's add that now, so
that's in Menus &amp; Toolbars, and then the remainder of the interface I want to resemble Windows Explorer.
So, I want to have a tree view over here, I want to have a list view over here, and I want to have some way
to resize these two controls relative to each other.
So coming back to Visual Studio, I'll go open up the Toolbox, and then down here there is a section called Containers.
Now we haven't really talked about Container controls, so let's cover that first.
Let me put a panel onto the form, and then let me just change the background color of the panel to something
other than the color of the form, I don't know it doesn't really matter, Cornsilk, there that works.
Alright, now let me go and drag and drop some controls onto the form, so let's put a textbox on there,
and then let's put, I don't know, it doesn't really matter, a label, and how about a button?
Alright, now, if I go and highlight the panel and then move it, notice that the controls move with it.
So the panel is what's called a Container control, meaning that it has its own controls collection, and
controls you put on the container are children of the container. So the panel is part of the forms controls
collection, but the TextBox, the button, and the label, are part of the panel controls collection.
And again, if I move the panel they move, and if I delete the panel they go away.
In this instance we're going to use a container control called the SplitContainer.
So if I come down to Containers, here's SplitContainer, and I'll put that on my form, and here we have a
panel on the left side, a splitter, and then a panel on the right side, and then now all we need to do is put
the tree view over here on the left side and dock that into the panel, and then put my list view over here
on the right side, and then dock that into that panel. And now I have my application, so when I press F5
here, if I resize, everything resizes, and I have the splitter, or I can change the relative size of the
preview and the list view controls. So that gives us the form layout that we want.
In the next demo we'll look at populating the tree view control.