In this demo, we'll populate the tree view in our Explorer-Style application.
So since we're building an Explorer-Style application, we'll build something that looks like Explorer.
What I'll do is over here in the tree view; I'll show all the folders underneath the user's My Documents folder,
and then when the user selects a folder we'll show the files for that folder over here in the list view.
Before we write the code to populate the tree view, let's take a look at how the tree view works.
The tree view contains a set of nodes and those nodes are laid out in a tree structure; so in this case,
Libraries is a node, Documents is a node, My Documents is a node, and so on.
And the tree view has a nodes collection, and each node has a nodes collection.
So if I add a node into the nodes collection for the tree view, it becomes a root node, that's a node that
has no parent, and if I add a node into the nodes collection of another node, for example, if I add
ArchitectureExplorer into the nodes collection for Visual Studio 2012, then ArchitectureExplorer becomes a
child of Visual Studio 2012. So what we'll be doing is adding My Documents as a root node, and then build up
the nodes below that by recursively traversing its child folders. Okay, so coming back to Visual Studio,
let's add the Form_Load event handler, and in here I want to create the tree node for My Documents,
so that's Dim docs As New TreeNode, and the constructor or one of the overloads for the constructor takes the
text that's going to be shown for that node, so that's "My Documents."
And then I want to store the path to the My Documents folder in the tagged property for the tree node control;
again the tag property is a property we can use to store any value that we like; we'll store the path to the
folder so that we can eventually get the files for that folder when the user clicks on the associated tree node.
So that's just docs.Tag = My.Computer.FileSystem.SpecialDirectories.MyDocuments, and then we'll add the
MyDocuments node into the nodes collection of the tree view, so that's TreeView1.Nodes.Add(docs).
So that adds the root node, now we want to add the child nodes by traversing the folder structure underneath My Documents.
So we'll create a function called GetFolders that will do that, and the parameter to GetFolders will be the tree node.
So now let's create GetFolders, so that's Private Sub GetFolders, and the parameter is a tree node,
so (node As TreeNode). And the first thing I'll do inside of GetFolders is to get an object that represents
a directory associated with this tree node, so that's Dim dir As New, and the type I want is called DirectoryInfo.
And then I'll just use Ctrl . to add the import statement that I need, and then the parameter here is the
path to the folder, and we've stored that in the tagged property of the node, so that's just node.Tag.
So now that I have the object representing the folder, I can use its GetDirectory method to get a list
of the child folders, and then we'll iterate through that and create nodes for each of those.
So that's For Each childDir In dir, that's the parent directory, dir.GetDirectories.
I want to create a new tree node that will be a child of the node parameter, so that's Dim childNode As New TreeNode,
and the text of the tree node will be the name of the folder, so that's childDir.Name, and then just like I
did with the My Documents, I want to store the folder path in the Tag property, so that's
childNode.Tag = childDir.FullName, and then I want to add the new node into the nodes collection of the node parameter;
so node.Nodes.Add(childNode). So this code will get us all the folders underneath My Documents, but we also
want to show their child folders, so we'll call GetFolders recursively, so GetFolders, passing in the childNode.
Alright, so that should be enough to let us test out our work, so let's press F5,
and there's My Documents, and there's Fiddler, IIS Express, and My Music, but that's it.
And if we come over here, we can see that there are a few more folders here that don't show up in our application.
So let's stop and then flip back over to
Visual Studio, and then let's take a look at the Output window here.
And here we see a first chance exception of type 'System.UnauthorizedAccessException' occurred in mscorlib.dll.
So an error occurred, but it wasn't surfaced into Visual Studio or our application, and that's actually the
behavior you get in your FormLoad event handler, unless you specifically trap for exceptions, they get silently handled.
So what we can do is just modify our GetFolders method, so let's add a Try Catch block in here, and then
let's take our For loop and put it inside of the Try block, and then in the Catch block, let's just show the
error message, so that's MsgBox(ex.Message). Alright, so now let's try again, F5, and there we get access
to the path Documents\My Music' is denied, Documents\My Picture' is denied, and Documents\My Videos' is denied.
But now we can see we have all of the folders, including these three where we had the errors.
So the reason we're getting these errors is because My Music, My Pictures, and My Videos aren't really
folders under My Documents, they're actually links to other folders, so we just need to filter those out as
we go through and populate the folders structure here. I can do that by checking the attributes of the
folder to see if it's hidden. So in here I'll add If childDir.Attributes.HasFlag(fileAttributes.Hidden)
Then Continue For, so just skip this folder. Alright, so now if we run, we don't get any errors, and we get
the folders that we want for our application. And then one last cosmetic change, when the application starts
up, I don't want my folders to be collapsed, I want them to be expanded, so then just up here under
GetFolders I'll say docs.Expand, press F5 one last time, and there we get the behavior that we want.
Okay, so that's populating the tree view; in the next demo we'll take a look at populating the list view.