In this demo we'll add the code to add the items and images to the list view in our Explorer-Style application.
So let's come over to Windows Explorer and take a look
at how the list view works. As the user clicks on Folders here in the tree view, the items that are in that
folder are shown in the list view; in this case it's Folders and Files; in our application we'll only be
showing the Files. Now notice that each item has an icon and a caption, that's one important
characteristic of the list view. Another important characteristic is you can switch the views.
So here we have Medium Icons, I can show Large Icons, and notice the only difference here is the size of the icon.
I can go to Small Icons; again the same thing, just the way they're laid out and the size of the icon.
And we also have a view called Details view. So here we have the icon and the caption for the item, but we
also have some additional information about the item; in this case it's the date modified, the type, and the size.
These additional items are called the sub-items of the main item.
So in our application we'll add an event handler from when the user selects one of the items out of the tree
view; when they do we'll find the information about the files contained in that folder, and then display them
in the list view using the view selected by the user. Okay, let's switch back over to Visual Studio,
and then double-click on the tree view to add the event handler for the AfterSelect event, this is the one I
want to handle, and the first thing I want to do is create a DirectoryInfo object to represent the folder the
user selected in the tree view, so that's Dim dir As New DirectoryInfo, and here I need to pass the path to
the folder, that's stored in the Tag property of the selected tree view node.
I can get access to the selected tree view node using the event arguments for the event handler, so that's e.Node.Tag.
Then I want to clear the items in the list view, so that's ListView1.Items.Clear, then I want to look
through the files in the selected folder and create a list view item for each one of those,
so that's For Each File In dir.GetFiles; oh and actually let me rename this variable because the IntelliSense
is confusing the file variable with the file type, so just so there's no confusion, let's call it thisFile.
Alright, so now I want to create the list view item, so that's Dim item As New ListViewItem, and one of the
overloads for the constructor takes the caption for the item, that will be the name of the file,
so thisFile.Name, and then we can add the item into the items collection for the list view,
so that's ListView1.Items.Add(item). Alright, so at this point we can run, let's press F5, and then pick
a folder here, how about Reflector. So right now we're getting the captions for the items but not their
images; so let's add that functionality. Alright, so let's get out of full screen, and then come back over
to the Designer, and let's take a look at some of the properties of the list view control.
So the first is View, which is what is the default view; here we can see the options; we'll leave it at LargeIcon.
And then as I scroll up, we can see there's a SmallImageList, and then further up there is a property called LargeImageList.
So the images associated with the items in the list view are stored in an image list control.
So if we go to the Toolbox here, and then open up the Components section, we'll see that we find the ImageList control.
So let's put two of these onto our form; since they're not visible they go down here in the Component area.
One of these is going to store the large images for our list view, so we'll call this guy the LargeImageList,
and we'll set the ColorDepth here to 32, and then the size of the images this will store will be 32,32.
And then as you can imagine this one's going to be the SmallImageList, and the ColorDepth will be 32, and the
size of the images will stay at 16,16. So now if we come over to the list view here, I can set the two properties;
so one was the LargeImageList, so I'll set that to the LargeImageList control, and the other was the
SmallImageList, so I'll set that to the SmallImageList control. We won't be using the SmallImageList right
now, but we will be using it momentarily.
Alright, so let's go back to our event handler and add the code to populate the image list and to associate
images with list view items. Now at this point you've probably seen me type enough code, so I'm going to
start copying and pasting in code snippets. Each item in an image list has an index in a key, and you can
reference it either way; we'll be storing images associated with files, so we'll use the file extension as the key.
So the first thing we'll do is check to see whether or not the image list already has an image associated
with the file extension. If it doesn't, then we'll use the method Icon.ExtracAssociatedIcon, to get the icon
associated with the file in Windows, and then we'll add that into the image list.
And then finally we'll tell the list view item that its ImageKey is the file extension, so we'll then go to
the appropriate image list and get the icon it needs, depending on the current view.
Now there's one more line of code we need to add. For almost all files in Windows, if the file has the same
extension it has the same icon. But for executables that's not the case, so what we'll do up here is we'll
remove the item in the image list associated with the executable or .exe extension.
Now there could be some case where a single folder holds multiple files with the .exe extension, and they
have different icons, but we're not going to deal with that scenario in our app.
Alright, so let's press F5 now, and now we can see we not only get the caption, but we get the icon
associated with the file. So that covers adding items and images to our list view, so we'll end this part of
the demo here, and then in the next demo we'll take a look at supporting multiple views, including the details view.