In this demo we'll enable users to change views in the list view in our Explorer-Style application, and we'll
add support for the details view. So just one note before I get started, I did modify the code a little bit.
In the AfterSelect event handler for the tree view, I'm populating both the large and small image lists.
Now getting back to the views, I want something in the UI that the user can use to switch between views,
and for this we'll use the Toolbar, so I'll add a label, and I'll just set this label, let me go to full
screen here, and I'll just set the text of the label to View, and then beside this I'll add a ComboBox,
and I'll call this the ViewToolStripComboBox, so let me just make this a little bit bigger so we have some
more space here, so ViewToolStripComboBox. And in here I want to have the different views it will support,
so I'll come down to the Items, and this will be Large Icons, Small Icons, and finally Details.
And then when the user selects an item out of the ComboBox, I want to switch the view in the list view.
To do that I'll add an event handler for the SelectedIndexChanged event, so I'll scroll down here,
SelectedIndexChanged, and now I just need a Select statement to change the view based on what the user selected.
So if they selected Large Icons, I'll change the view to be Large Icons in the list view, Small Icons in Details.
And coming back to the ComboBox, I want to set it, so again let me get out of full screen here, when the
application first starts up we see large icons, because that's the default view here.
So if I come over to the properties, what I want to set is the SelectedIndex, and we can't do that here in
the Properties Windows, so I'll have to do it in the Form_Load event, and here let me just again resize this.
So I want to say ViewToolStripComboBox.SelectedIndex = 0, the first item, which is large icons.
Alright, so with that changed, I can press F5,
and there's large icons, actually let me just go to some place that has a few more files in here,
Projects, our SDI application, and then here, okay there's a few more, and then we can go to Small Icons,
and then we can go to Details. And you notice nothing shows in Details here, and that's because we haven't
told the list view what columns we want to have in the details view, so let's do that now.
So coming back over to the form designer, I can click on the list view, and I believe there is a property
called Columns, and there's this Columns Editor here; I find it's easier to just define the columns in code,
so I'll do that here in the Form-Load. So we'll have three columns; one is the name of the file, one is the
date modified, and then the last is the size. The second parameter indicates how wide the column should be,
and the third parameter indicates its alignment. So if we run again,
and then go find a folder, so Projects-SDI-SDI, and then switch to Details view, now we can see in the Name
column we have the icon and we have the file name, but we don't have the date modified or size because we
haven't populated these yet, and that's the last step to complete the application.
So as I mentioned, when working with the list view and details view, this is the item information, and then
these are considered the sub-items, so I need to add the information for these columns as sub-items of the
list view item. So coming back to our code here, down in the TreeView1_AfterSelect, once I create the item
I want to populate the sub-items. So the first thing I'll do is create a variable that gets the
LastWriteTime for the file, again I've changed the file name here so let me just fix that, and then in the
first sub-time for the list view item, I put down the date and time it was last modified, so I'm going to
write out the ShortDateString and then a space, and then the ShortTimeString.
And then in the second sub-item, I want to write out the size of the file in kilobytes, so I'll take the
file size in bytes, divide by 1024, get the ceiling of that value, and then append KB to the string.
So with that done, now if we go to F5, and again go to our SDI application here, and then switch to details view,
we have the item information populated, but we also have the date modified and the file size.
And with that done, our Explorer-Style application is now complete.