In this series of demos we'll take a look at the DataSources Window and the Drag-and-Drop data binding tools
included in Visual Studio and Windows Forms. We'll see how the use of these tools automates much of what
we've done in terms of data binding up to this point in the course.
I'll be building two projects, one that uses LINQ to SQL, and one that uses type DataSets, so I can highlight
the similarities and differences when using the data binding tools with these two different DataSources.
In this demo we'll create the Visual Studio projects, and setup and configure the DataSources.
So in this instance of Visual Studio, I'll choose File-New-Project, I'll create a Windows Forms Application,
we'll call this LinqDragDrop, and click OK, and then we'll create our LINQ to SQL model in exactly the same
way we did earlier in this module. So I'll right-click on the project, choose Add-New Item; in the Data
section I'll choose LINQ to SQL classes, I'll name this Northwind, click Add, and then in my designer here,
I'll drag and drop the Categories and Products table from the Data Connections in my Server Explorer.
So here's my Northwind database, and I'm going to drag and drop Categories and Products.
Alright, so that creates the model here in our LINQ to SQL project.
Now let's come over to our DataSet project and create it, so File-New Project, Windows Forms, this will be
DataSetDragDrop, and click OK, and then now I'll come over to the DataSources window here, and I'll pin it,
and I'll choose Add New Data Source. It's going to ask us what DataSource type we're going to be using;
I'm going to be getting data from a database, so I'll click Next; what kind of database model do I want to use?
I want to use a DataSet, so click Next. Then it's asking me which data connection should the application use
to connect to the database, and this is showing me the data connections out of the Server Explorer, which we
just saw a moment ago. So this is the same connection we used when we created our LINQ to SQL model.
So I'll click Next. It's now asking me if we want to store the connection string for the Northwind database
in the settings for the application, and we do; this happened in our LINQ to SQL model, it just happened
automatically, we weren't prompted, so I'll click Next. Visual Studio has now gone to our database and found
the different objects in there; these are the same objects we saw in the Server Explorer, so I want to expand
Tables and choose Categories and Products, just as we did in our LINQ to SQL model, and the DataSet name,
NorthwindDataSet is just fine. I'll now click Finish to create the type DataSet.
So over here in our DataSources window, we now have the Categories and Products tables shown; we'll see how
we can use those in just a moment.
And then over in our Solution Explorer, we see we now have NorthwindDataSet.xsd.
So if I click on it and then choose to Show All Files, and then expand it, you'll see there's a file called
NorthwindDataSet.Designer.vb or Designer.cs. So let's open that up and unpin DataSources, and then use
Ctrl ? to bring up the Navigate To, and search for Products. So you'll see there's a class called
ProductsDataTable, and there's also a class called ProductsTableAdapter.
And if we search instead for Categories, you'll see the same thing, so there's CategoriesDataTable,
CategoriesTableAdapter, there's also CategoriesRow, there was a ProductsRow; so these are the strongly type
DataTable, DataAdapter, and DataRow classes that were generated by the wizard.
And the definitions of these classes all exist here in this Designer.vb or Designer.cs file.
Now getting back to the DataSources window and the Drag-and-Drop data binding tools, here in our type DataSet
project, we've setup our DataSources window, let's do the same thing over here in our LINQ project.
I'll save the model and close it, and then I'll go to DataSources and pin it, and I'll choose Add New Data Source,
and in this case our DataSource is going to be our model, so I'll choose Object, and then click Next.
Visual Studio is going to reflect on our project and show the types contained within, and we want the
Category and Product objects that were generated as part of our LINQ to SQL model.
And now I can click Finish, and now we have the Category and Product objects in our DataSources window.
That concludes this demo. In the next demo we'll take a look at the basics of Drag-and-Drop data binding.