Now we can take a look at the Drag-and-Drop data binding. We'll start out with the simplest case where
we'll use all of the data in the Products table. So I'll come over here to Products in the DataSources,
and I'll drop this little dropdown, and I'll make sure that DataGridView is selected, and then I'll drag and
drop Product onto my form. So you can see that several things happened; a DataGridView control was added,
a BindingNavigator control was added, and a BindingSource was added.
If we take a look at the properties of the BindingSource, we can see that we're indicating that the Product
class that's part of our LINQ to SQL model is the DataSource for the BindingSource.
If we come over to the DataGridView, and open up the smart tag here, we can see that this has been bound to
the ProductsBindingSource. We can also see that in the Properties for the control in the Properties Window,
and if we take a look at the BindingNavigator, it's also been bound to the ProductsBindingSource.
Now before I run this, let's come over to our DataSet project, and then expand both Categories and Products;
you can see we have a similar view to what we had over here on the LINQ side, and then I'll go to Products,
I'll drop down the dropdown, I'll choose DataGridView, and I'll drag and drop Products onto our form.
So you can see we get a similar behavior, but there are a few extra things now on the form that we didn't
have in our LINQ to SQL example. So we have our DataGridView, we have the BindingNavigator, we have the
BindingSource, but we also have a NorthwindDataSet, we have a ProductsTableAdapter, and we have this thing
called the TableAdapterManager. I'll explain the purpose of the TableAdapterManager in just a bit.
Now taking a look at the properties of these controls, our ProductsBindingSource is bound to the
NorthwindDataSet, and its DataMember has been set to Products, so it's a Products DataTable inside of this DataSet.
And then taking a look at the DataGridView, this is bound to the ProductsBindingSource.
And if we take a look at the properties for the BindingNavigator, and scroll down, we can see that its
BindingSource is also the ProductsBindingSource. Now when we use Drag-and-Drop data binding with the type
DataSet, the designer also omits some code into the code behind for the form.
So if we take a look here, in the Form_Load, the code has been added to Fill the Products table in the
NorthwindDataSet using the Fill method of the ProductsTableAdapter.
And then also the Click event handler for the Save button in the BindingNavigator has been implemented,
so when it's clicked, we Validate the form, we make sure the BindingSource ends any current edits, and then
we have the TableAdapterManager Update the NorthwindDataSet. So what is the TableAdapterManager?
Well it's a type that was generated along with our NorthwindDataSet.
As I mentioned, when we use the DataSources window to generate our Categories and Products and DataSources,
we also got the NorthwindDataSet. And as we've seen previously, in order to populate a DataSet and take
the changes from the DataSet and push them back into the database, we need DataAdapters.
So two DataAdapters were created, one for the Products table and one for the Categories table.
But because the DataSource's wizard was able to look at the underlying database, it was also able to generate
a sort of super DataAdapter, which is a TableAdapterManager. It knows about the ProductsTableAdapter,
it knows about the CategoriesTableAdapter, and it also knows there's a foreign key relationship between
Products and Categories. So the generated code inside the TableAdapterManager is able to update both
Categories and Products, keeping the foreign key and other database constraints in mind.
So when working with a type DataSet, we can make a single call to update all the tables in the DataSet via
the TableAdapterManager, instead of having to make a call for each table.
Alright, so now that we've seen what was generated, let's actually run our program.
I'll get out of full screen and come back to the designer here, and I'll do one thing, I'll dock this in
the Parent Container, and then I'll click F5 or press F5 to the run the program.
And there we can see our form with the grid populated, can expand this, we can see more information, I can
use the navigator here to navigate through the results set, I can go to the end, I can go to the beginning.
If I go to the end here and then pick Test 7, click on that, and then click Delete, that gets deleted from
the DataSet, so if I stopped and run again, that delete shouldn't have been persisted because we just made
it in-memory; alright so if I go to the end there's Test 7 again.
But if I click on Test 7 and then click Delete, and then click Save to push that change back to the database,
and then get out of here, and then press F5, again expand this, go to the end, we can see that Test 7 has been removed.
Alright, so that's the basics of the DataSet project, now let's come over to our LINQ project.
In the case of the LINQ project, we don't get the same code behind generation we had in the DataSet example.
So, if I come over to the form and then go to its code behind,
you can see we don't get anything. So in this case we'll need to write the code to populate the form and
persist any changes. Alright, so let's get the form populated.
I'll come back to the designer, and then double-click here to add the Form_Load event handler, and then I'll
create an instance of our LINQ to SQL DataContext, so that's Dim context As New NorthwindDataContext,
and then I'll set the DataSource on the products BindingSource to be the Products table off the DataContext,
so that's ProductBindingSource.DataSource = context.Products. So now I can press F5,
and again we have the data coming out of the database; I can expand the form here, again I can use the
navigator to navigate through the results set, I can go to the end, I can go to the beginning, and so on.
Now to complete the demo I want to add the Update functionality to our LINQ project.
But to do this I'm going to have to do something I told you not to do, and that's use our DataContext at the class level.
Now I can do the unit-of-work pattern here, but unfortunately there's a lot more code that I want to show you
in this very simple demo, so I'm just going to put this context as a Private field in the form,
so private _context As New NorthwindDataContext, and then I just need to set this to _context,
and then I'll come over to the designer here, and I'll enable this button, so I'll click on the button,
and choose Enabled = True, and then I'll add the event handler for the button, and then I'll come back over
here and just grab most of this, or at least the first two lines of the code we have in the Save here because
I want to do the same things over in my LINQ project. And then here instead of using the TableAdapterManager
I'll use the context, and it's just _context.SubmitChanges. Alright, I just need to change
ProductsBindingSource to ProductBindingSource in this case, and there we are good to go.
So now I can press F5, I can expand my form here, let's come down to the bottom.
Alright, so for Test 4, let's set the Supplier to 2 instead of 1, and let's set the Unit Price to something,
you know, really high just so that we'll sort of be able to recognize it, and then let's come in here and
delete Test 8, and then finally let's add a new item, so this will be Test 10, Supplier is 1, Category is 1,
this is some value there, this is a number, that's a number, that's a number, that's a number, and actually
let's just check Discontinued here for this one. Alright, so Test 4, Supplier is 2, a very high unit price.
Test 10 is our new item, and we deleted one other item. Now let's save our changes, let's close the form
down, press F5, expand the form, and then go to the end. There's Test 4, there's the SupplierID, there is
our big Unit Price, and there is Test 10. Alright, so that's the simple case of using the DataSources window
and using the Drag-and-Drop data binding. In the next demo we'll take a look at Drag-and-Drop data binding
with more traditional data entry controls like labels, textboxes, and checkboxes.