In this demo we'll modify our Drag-and-Drop data binding applications to use the Details view instead
of the DataGridView. I'll start here in our DataSet application, I'll come to our DataGridView, and I'll
just delete it. And then I'll come over to the DataSources window, I'll pin it open, and then I'll go to
Products, and I'm going to switch the dropdown here from DataGridView to Details view.
And then for each of the properties and products, it shows you which data entry element it's going to use to show that.
So these are all textboxes and this is a checkbox. But we have some control over how this is shown.
So, for example, if I don't want to show ProductID, I can click on it and I can just choose None here.
I'll do the same for SupplierID, and ReorderLevel, and then for CategoryID and ProductName, I want these to
be ReadOnly. So I'll change CategoryID to be a Label instead of a textbox, and for ProductName I'll modify
the textbox after I've built my form. So now that I've configured the Details view the way I want it,
I can just drag products onto the form, and now instead of getting a grid, I get a set of more traditional
data entry controls. And now I can just clean up the layout a little bit, so I'm going to take these and
lasso them and just move them down a little bit. And then here I want this to be a little bit bigger,
this textbox; I also want it to be ReadOnly, so I'll come down to ReadOnly and set that to True.
And then for the discontinued checkbox, I'll get rid of the text here, and that should be good.
So let's hit F5. So now instead of working with all the products in one big grid, I'm working with
individual items, and again I can use the BindingNavigator to scroll through the items, and I can go to the
end like we did before, and for Test 10, I've got 100, 10, and 10, let's change that to 300, 30, and 30,
and then go back one. And for Test 4 let's go ahead and delete, and then let's save our changes, and stop
the program, run again, go to the end; there's Test 10, 300, 30, 30, and if I go back one, now we're actually
into an original item, not one of our test items. And if I close this program down here, and then come over
to our LINQ example, I can do exactly the same thing. So I'll remove the data grid, open up DataSources,
pin the window, switch to Details view, set the CategoryID = None, set the SupplierID = None, set the
ReorderLevel = None, set the ProductID, oops I didn't want CategoryID = None, I wanted it to be a Label,
it's ProductID I wanted to be None. And then I can drag Product onto my form.
And notice I not only get the product information, I also get information about the associated category.
So here in the LINQ to SQL side, it picked up that there's a two-way relationship; categories have products,
and products are associated to a category. Now in this case I don't want the category information on the
screen, so I'll just lasso it and delete it. And then I'll do a little bit of cleanup here, so I want
Discontinued to be at the bottom not up there, and I want Product Name to be a little bit higher, and then
I want Category ID to be below that, that looks good, and then I want to lasso the entire thing and then just
move it up over here, move this or resize that, and then set it to be ReadOnly, press F5,
and I can get exactly the same behavior I had in my DataSet example.
Now coming back to our form designer, when I dragged and dropped the controls from the DataSources window
over, I got the Category here related to the Product; let's explore this a little bit further but in the other way.
So I'm going to add a new form to my project, I'll right-click and choose Add-Windows Form.
And now what I'm going to do is start with Categories, so I'll go to Category and say that I want Details,
and then I'll drag and drop Category onto my form. I'll just move these controls over a little bit, get rid
of this Length label and textbox, and make my form a little bit bigger, and then I'm going to go to Products
here, but not the product entity we used before; I'm going to go to the products associated with the categories.
So here I'm going to say I want this in DataGridView, and then I'll drag and drop this on my form here,
and just place it like this. And then to ensure this control resizes when the form resizes, I'll just change
its Anchor property, so this will be right, bottom, and left. Alright, so now let's examine our controls.
We have the DataGridview, we have the textboxes, the labels, the BindingNavigator, we have a
CategoryBindingSource, and we also have a ProductsBindingSource. So, for the CategoryBindingSource, it says
here that the DataSource is the Category entities in our LINQ to SQL model, but for the ProductsBindingSource
it says that the DataSource is the CategoryBindingSource, so this BindingSource is binding to that BindingSource.
And then back in the ProductsBindingSource, this is binding to the Products collection coming out of the
CategoryBindingSource. So in our LINQ to SQL model, categories are related to products by a foreign key in
the database, so category entities have a products collection property, which represent the products in that category.
So now if I press F5, we can see I get the, whoops sorry I need to change the startup form, so I want to use
Form2, so I'll go to My Project and double-click and change the startup form to Form2, and now press F5 here,
oh and I need to change my code behind, sorry I'm not in the DataSet example, I'm in the LINQ to SQL example.
So let me go back to my form, double-click here, and like before I'll create a field to represent our
DataContext, so Private _context As New NortwindDataContext, and then down here in Form_Load, I'll say that
the CategoryBindingSource.DataSource = _context.Categories. And then if I wanted to make this form so you
could edit, I could go back to the form design, click on the Save button in the BindingNavigator, come up and
set Enabled = True, add the event handler, and then take the code we had in Form1, and just copy and paste it into Form2.
And in this case, now this is not the ProductsBindingSource, it is the CategoryBindingSource.
Alright, so now I can press F5, and there we go. So there's our category information, and there are the
products associated with the category. Oh, I set my anchor wrong, but that's not important.
And now here if I navigate through the categories, you can see that as the categories change the products
change because we're only showing the products associated with the current category.
So that's our LINQ example. We can do exactly the same thing over here in our DataSet side, so right-click,
Add-Windows Form, click Add, resize the form, open up Categories, I want Details view, drag and drop that
on the form, there's my category, data entry fields are my category controls, and then go to the products
related to the categories, DataGridView, drag and drop on the form over here, and then set the Anchor.
And in this case because I'm in a DataSet, the code I need in the code behind is given to me automatically,
so I can just press F5 to run, and now I'm able to cycle through, whoops again sorry, I forgot to change the
startup form to Form2. Now press F5, and now I can get exactly the same behavior I saw over on the LINQ side.
And to finish up this demo, I'll create a form similar to the one we had in our earlier data binding modules.
So I'll come to our DataSet project, I'll right-click, and I'll choose to Add a new form, and I'll just
resize the form a little bit, and then we'll go to our ToolBox, actually, sorry, I want our DataSources
window, and then I'll pin that. So here I want the Categories, and I want the Products, but I don't actually
want the controls right now. I just use the drag and drop to get the DataSet, the DataAdapter is all setup,
I'll also remove the BindingNavigator. Now I'll come over to the Toolbox and I'll pin that open, and I'll
unpin DataSources, and then here in the Common Controls I want a dropdown, so we'll put a ComboBox here.
And then I also want a ListBox, so I'll grab that and put that over here.
And then what I can do is use the smart tags on these controls to hook them up to the different BindingSources.
So here I'll say that I want to data bind the ComboBox, the Data Source will be the CategoriesBindingSource,
the Display Member will be the CategoryName. And then here in the ListBox, I'll say that I want to data bind,
I want my Data Source to be the ProductsBindingSource, and I want the Display Member to be the ProductName.
And then finally I'll unpin the Toolbox, come back to DataSources, change products here to Details, and then
drag and drop this over on this side of the form here, and then just move those sort of in line with the ListBox.
So now when I run I should be able to choose the category out of the dropdown; that'll show the products in
the ListBox, and as I scroll through the ListBox we should see the details for the selected item over here
in the textboxes and the checkbox. So let's give that a shot. I'll press F5, oh and again, I need to change
the startup form, so back to my project, change startup form to Form3, now press F5, and here are the
Beverages, and if I switch to Produce, here are the Produce items, if I scroll through these you see we get
the information over here, and then here are our Seafood items.